<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="stylesheet.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD peattie.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include/peattie.dtd">

<TEI id="ep.essay.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Defence of Fine Writing</title>
<title type="sub"></title>
<author n="Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935">Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935</author>
<principal>George-Bloomfield, Susanne, 1947-</principal>
<editor></editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Zach Bajaber</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Nebraska Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</publisher>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>ep.essay.001</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<!-- <notesStmt>
<note></note>
</notesStmt> -->

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author n="Peattie, Elia W.">Elia W. Peattie</author>
<title level="a">A Defence of Fine Writing</title>
<title level="j">The Critic</title>
<biblScope type="volume">42</biblScope>
<date when="1903-06">June 1903</date>
<biblScope type="pages">546-547</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

<!-- <notesStmt>
<note></note>
</notesStmt> -->
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords n="genre">
<term>Short Story</term>
</keywords>
</textClass></profileDesc>

<!-- <encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc> -->

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-11-24</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted from html</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>200y-mm-dd</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Transcribed by Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Original Transcription</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1>

<pb n="546" />
<head type="main">A Defence of Fine Writing</head>


<byline>by Elia W. Peattie</byline>

<p>I SAW recently, in an article by a popular critic, a rebuke for a

young novelist because of "fine writing."  The critic said the one

fault of the novelist was his fondness for that sort of thing, and

expressed the hope that he would sooner or later become conscious

of his mistake.  I have not read the books of the writer to whom

reference was made, but as he was classed with George Meredith I

imagine that his work must have been really literary, and I am

willing to admit &#8212; without undue urging &#8212; that I am not one of

those who shy at beauty, even when I see it lying right beside the

road.</p>

<p>A good many folk have got into the way of considering

matter-of-factness consummate good form.  They cannot tolerate

anything pronounced and would no more indulge in a passionate or

exceedingly pictorial sentence than they would drive down Fifth

Avenue in a scarlet and gold coach drawn by piebald horses.  They

are as plain as a tailor-made suit in their manner of writing, and it is

evident that they are responsible for the withdrawal of Literature

from her place among the Arts, and her dubious installation among

the drab Utilities.  There she sits, poor girl, tight-laced,

conventional, shy, and dull, looking with wistful but bewildered

gaze into that luminous past when she was held to be Queen of all

the Arts.  Fair days, those!  Her courtiers hung pearls about her

neck, there were always dewy blossoms on her head, and the

'broidery of her robes betrayed the devotion of her handmaidens.</p>

<p>Now, marry come up, we must beware lest we decorate our

ideas, we dare apostrophize nothing, we are inoculated against

passion, and fantasy is as out of favor as embezzlement!  It is not

thought quite sane to be enthusiastic about anything; to be ardent is

as great an offence as to be unsophisticated, and any one who is

eloquent may expect the sardonic lifting of brows at his expense. 

Who supposes for a moment, that any one as excessive as

Shakespeare would be proposed at any Writers' Club were he to

appear among us to-day?  It is quite certain that the critic quoted at

the first of this article would have slashed him merrily for his

puerility in daring to be "fine."</p>

<p>I do not say, of course, that the Continental Europeans are as

heavy and self-conscious as all this, for really M. Maeterlinck

seems more or less indifferent to public opinion, and probably

would not apologize though he were caught in the very act of

passionately and eloquently uttering a lovely truth; and quite a

number of Frenchmen, Italians, Germans, Norwegians, and

Russians are still unashamed when they depict some great character,

portray weird or splendid scenes, or present a moving play.  It is

only we Anglo-Saxons who are so stiff, so ugly, and so shy.  Can it

be that we are afraid that we shall become artists and therefore

disreputables?  The danger is slight.  Or it may be that we fear a

soulful outburst may proclaim us provincials.  But, after all, souls

are not exclusively suburban affairs.</p>

<p>If the creative literary worker is so circumscribed, try to fancy

in what cramped quarters the critic must abide!  He is allowed but

one activity &#8212; that of throwing cold water.  His praise is often as

dampening as his fault-finding.  Pronouncing upon an earnest and

eager book, he says, perhaps: "The author appears to be unduly

agitated about his subject.  He should learn to take well-known facts

and his own none too lofty fancies with more calmness."  Or,

speaking of a glowing biography, he utters this easy cynicism: "The

author has permitted himself to become an advocate for his subject. 

The book is eulogistic, and not to be classed with serious works on

this theme."  A new poet appears and the critic is distinctly

annoyed.  "We fancy," he writes, "that we discern the influences of

certain Victorians in this young man's

<pb n="547" />

work.  This is well enough, and we commend the tidiness of his

versification, but we suggest more caution in simile and phrase, and

look to a moderation of adolescent enthusiasms."</p>

<p>In the class-room it is no better.  There are exceptions, of

course, but the average instructor in English is the Discourager of

Genius, the Slayer of Talent.  It is a common thing for originality to

be held up to ridicule before a class, and anything like passion of

utterance would be considered fit subject for professorial mirth.  It

is not in such places, surely that inspiration will be found.  It is not

here that the writer will learn to express himself with unreserve and

delight.</p>

<p>"Writing," said Sir Walter Scott, "is a habit.  My brother

Thomas could have written much better than I, but he never formed

the habit."</p>

<p>This is a substantial half of the truth, and the one unquestioned

excuse for courses in English is that they may get students in the

habit of writing.  If they get them out of the habit of it, they will not

have served their purpose.  A school for writers is not designed to

discourage students from writing, any more than a law school is

intended to deter students from practising law.  But as English is

taught in many university class-rooms, the professor appears in the

r&#244;le of the defender of literature against the attacks of the

mob &#8212; the class representing, of course, the murderous

<hi rend="italic">canaille</hi>.  This attitude is not conducive to producing

na&#239;ve and spontaneous utterances; it is not calculated to

invite a revelation of temperament, or to extract from the delicate

and reticent poet the visions of his soul.</p>

<p>It must be a sturdy talent and a robust egotism that can survive

these onslaughts of the professors of English; and adolescent

egotism is liable to be frail and budding talent tender.  Only a very

melodramatic mind can find pleasure in contemplating the tragedies

of the class-room.</p>

<p>The question is, How is the Anglo-Saxon to accustom himself

to beauty?  Could he, by the wearing of smoked glasses, mitigate

the glare till his eyes became strengthened sufficiently for him to

look at loveliness without blinking?  Since he is an idealist in the

matter of morals, may we not hope that he will presently cease to be

a literalist in matters of art?  If his imagination is appealed to by the

wizards of modern mechanics, the practical masters of physics, the

captains of commerce, can it not be touched also by the

impassioned and spiritual artist?  Must the delineator of life foever

feign that he finds the mortal experiences of men and women

commonplace, snug, smug, and trivial?  If the geographer is

permitted to tell tremendous tales, may not the poet be permitted to

do as much?  If the machinist sets the pulses throbbing with his

colossal engines, may not the novelist be allowed to rival him?</p>

<p>At any rate, these calm, mediocre, and cynic intelligences need

not endeavor to discomfit the enthusiasts with their easy

opprobrium.  It is pure shenanigan, and ought not to fool any one.</p>

<p>Moreover, there is one tremendous comfort.  The real genius

does not bother very much with the ideas of other men.  He is too

self-absorbed.  So perhaps he will never find out that his eloquence

is discountenanced by the trim critics of the capitals.  As for the

unhappy child of talent, it is different with him.  He has regard for

the critics.  He thinks about public opinion.  He is likely, under the

lash of the unimaginative reviewer of books, to fit into the lustreless

mosaic of the common scheme.  It is much more than probable that,

having little faith, he will blush for the beauty that burned in his

heart in the days when he first knew the joy of utterance, and that he

will become as literal, as cautious, as full of doubt and dulness as

the most cosmopolitan and sophisticated critic could desire.</p>



</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
