<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="stylesheet.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD peattie.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include/peattie.dtd" [

]>
<TEI id="ep.gs.0007">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Child of the Rain</title>
<title type="sub"></title>
<author n="Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935">Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935</author>
<principal>George-Bloomfield, Susanne, 1947-</principal>
<editor></editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Zach Bajaber</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Nebraska Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</publisher>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>ep.gs.0007</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<!-- <notesStmt>
<note></note>
</notesStmt> -->

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author n="Peattie, Elia W.">Elia W. Peattie</author>
<title level="m">The Shape of Fear and Other Ghostly Tales</title>
<title level="a">A Child of the Rain</title>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<publisher>Macmillan</publisher>
<date value="1898">1898</date>
<series>Short Story Index Reprint Series</series>
<pubPlace>Freeport, NY</pubPlace>
<publisher>Books for Libraries Press</publisher>
<date value="1969">1969</date>
<biblScope type="pages">79-88</biblScope>
</bibl>

</sourceDesc>

<!-- <notesStmt>
<note></note>
</notesStmt> -->
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p>Note: I have omitted signature indicators and running heads.

In addition, I have made the following changes to the text:

<table>

<row><cell>PAGE</cell><cell>LINE</cell><cell>ORIGINAL</cell><cell>CHANGED TO</cell></row>

<row><cell>156</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>where as</cell><cell>were as</cell></row>

<row><cell>156</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>mouth</cell><cell>mouth.</cell></row>

<row><cell>165</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>Wedgwood</cell><cell>Wedgewood</cell></row>

<row><cell>166</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>Wedgwood</cell><cell>Wedgewood</cell></row>

<row><cell>167</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>surperfluous</cell><cell>superfluous</cell></row>

<row><cell>172</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>every</cell><cell>ever</cell></row>

<row><cell>173</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>Bogg</cell><cell>Boggs</cell></row>

</table>
</p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>


<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords n="genre">
<term>Short Story</term>
</keywords>
</textClass></profileDesc>



<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2009-02-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Vicki Martin</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Proofreading</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2008-11-17</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item></item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2007-10-31</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted from html</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>200y-mm-dd</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Transcribed by Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Original Transcription</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1>

<pb id="ep.gs.0007.01.jpg" n="79"/>

<head>A CHILD OF THE RAIN</head>

<p>IT was the night that Mona Meeks, the dressmaker, told him she

didn't love him.   He couldn't believe it at first, because he had so

long been accustomed to the idea that she did, and no matter how

rough the weather or how irascible the passengers, he felt a song in

his heart as he punched transfers, and rang his bell punch, and

signalled the driver when to let people off and on.</p>

<p>Now, suddenly, with no reason except a woman's, she had

changed her mind.   He dropped in to see her at five o'clock, just

before time for the night shift, and to give her two red apples he had

been saving for her. She looked at the apples as if they were

invisible and she could not see them, and <orig reg="standing">stand-

<pb id="ep.gs.0007.02.jpg" n="80"/>

ing</orig> in her disorderly little dressmaking parlor, with its cuttings and

scraps and litter of fabrics, she said:</p>

<p>"It is no use, John. I shall have to work here like this all my life

&#8212;work here alone. For I don't love you, John. No, I don't. I thought

I did, but it is a mistake."</p>

<p>"You mean it?" asked John, bringing up the words in a great

gasp.</p>

<p>"Yes," she said, white and trembling and putting out her hands

as if to beg for his mercy.  And then&#8212;big, lumbering fool&#8212;he

turned around and strode down the stairs and stood at the corner in

the beating rain waiting for his car. It came along at length,

spluttering on the wet rails and spitting out blue fire, and he took his

shift after a gruff "Good night" to Johnson, the man he

relieved.</p>

<p>He was glad the rain was bitter cold and drove in his face

fiercely.   He rejoiced at the cruelty of the wind, and when it hustled

pedestrians before it, lashing them, twisting 

<pb id="ep.gs.0007.03.jpg" n="81"/>

their clothes, and threatening their equilibrium, he felt amused.   He

was pleased at the chill in his bones and at the hunger that tortured

him. At least, at first he thought it was hunger till he remembered

that he had just eaten.  The hours passed confusedly. He had no

consciousness of time. But it must have been late,&#8212;near midnight,

&#8212;judging by the fact that there were few persons visible anywhere

in the black storm, when he noticed a little figure sitting at the far

end of the car.   He had not seen the child when she got on, but all

was so curious and wild to him that evening&#8212;he himself seemed to

himself the most curious and the wildest of all things&#8212;that it was

not surprising that he should not have observed the little

creature.</p>

<p>She was wrapped in a coat so much too large that it had become

frayed at the bottom from dragging on the pavement. Her hair hung

in unkempt stringiness about her bent shoulders, and her feet were

covered with 

<pb id="ep.gs.0007.04.jpg" n="82"/>

old arctics, many sizes too big, from which the soles hung

loose.</p>

<p>Beside the little figure was a chest of dark wood, with curiously

wrought hasps. From this depended a stout strap by which it could

be carried over the shoulders. John Billings stared in, fascinated by

the poor little thing with its head sadly drooping upon its breast, its

thin blue hands relaxed upon its lap, and its whole attitude so

suggestive of hunger, loneliness, and fatigue, that he made up his

mind he would collect no fare from it.</p>

<p>"It will need its nickel for breakfast," he said to himself. "The 

company can stand this for once. Or, come to think of it, I might

celebrate my hard luck. Here's to the brotherhood of failures!" And

he took a nickel from one pocket of his great-coat and dropped it in

another, ringing his bell punch to record the transfer.</p>

<p>The car plunged along in the darkness, and the rain beat more

viciously than ever in his face. The night was full of the rushing

sound 

<pb id="ep.gs.0007.05.jpg" n="83"/>

of the storm. Owing to some change of temperature the glass of the

car became obscured so that the young conductor could no longer

see the little figure distinctly, and he grew anxious about the

child.</p>

<p>"I wonder if it's all right," he said to himself. "I never saw living

creature sit so still."</p>

<p>He opened the car door, intending to speak with the child, but

just then something went wrong with the lights. There was a blue

and green flickering, then darkness, a sudden halting of the car, and

a great sweep of wind and rain in at the door. When, after a

moment, light and motion reasserted themselves, and Billings had

got the door together, he turned to look at the little passenger. But

the car was empty.</p>

<p>It was a fact. There was no child there&#8212;not even moisture on

the seat where she had been sitting.</p>

<p>"Bill," said he, going to the front door and addressing the driver,

"what became of that little kid in the old cloak?"</p>

<pb id="ep.gs.0007.06.jpg" n="84"/>

<p>"I didn't see no kid," said Bill, crossly. "For Gawd's sake, close

the door, John, and git that draught off my back."</p>

<p>"Draught!" said John, indignantly, "where's the draught?"</p>

<p>"You've left the hind door open," growled Bill, and John saw

him shivering as a blast struck him and ruffled the fur on his

bear-skin coat. But the door was not open, and yet John had to

admit to himself that the car seemed filled with wind and a strange

coldness.</p>

<p>However, it didn't matter. Nothing mattered! Still, it was as well

no doubt to look under the seats just to make sure no little

crouching figure was there, and so he did. But there was nothing. In

fact, John said to himself, he seemed to be getting expert in finding

nothing where there ought to be something.</p>

<p>He might have stayed in the car, for there was no likelihood of

more passengers that evening, but somehow he preferred going out 

<pb id="ep.gs.0007.07.jpg" n="85"/>

where the rain could drench him and the wind pommel him. How

horribly tired he was! If there were only some still place away from

the blare of the city where a man could lie down and listen to the

sound of the sea or the storm&#8212;or if one could grow suddenly old

and get through with the bother of living&#8212;or if&#8212;</p>

<p>The car gave a sudden lurch as it rounded a curve, and for a

moment it seemed to be a mere chance whether Conductor Billings

would stay on his platform or go off under those fire-spitting

wheels.   He caught instinctively at his brake, saved himself, and 

stood still for a moment, panting.</p>

<p>"I must have dozed," he said to himself.</p>

<p>Just then, dimly, through the blurred window, he saw again the

little figure of the child, its head on its breast as before, its blue

hands lying in its lap and the curious box beside it. John Billings

felt a coldness beyond the coldness of the night run through his

blood. Then, with a half-stifled cry, he 

<pb id="ep.gs.0007.08.jpg" n="86"/>

threw back the door, and made a desperate spring at the corner

where the eerie thing sat.</p>

<p>And he touched the green carpeting on the seat, which was quite

dry and warm, as if no dripping, miserable little wretch had ever

crouched there.</p>

<p>He rushed to the front door.</p>

<p>"Bill," he roared, "I want to know about that kid."</p>

<p>"What kid?"</p>

<p>"The same kid! The wet one with the old coat and the box with

iron hasps! The one that's been sitting here in the car!"</p>

<p>Bill turned his surly face to confront the young conductor.</p>

<p>"You've been drinking, you fool," said he. "Fust thing you know

you'll be reported."</p>

<p>The conductor said not a word. He went slowly and weakly

back to his post and stood there the rest of the way leaning against

the end of the car for support. Once or twice he muttered:</p>

<pb id="ep.gs.0007.09.jpg" n="87"/>

<p>"The poor little brat!"  And again he said, "So you didn't love

me after all!"</p>

<p>He never knew how he reached home, but he sank to sleep as

dying men sink to death. All the same, being a hearty young man,

he was on duty again next day but one, and again the night was

rainy and cold.</p>

<p>It was the last run, and the car was spinning along at its limit,

when there came a sudden soft shock. John Billings knew what that

meant.  He had felt something of the kind once before. He turned

sick for a moment, and held on to the brake.   Then he summoned

his courage and went around to the side of the car, which had

stopped. Bill, the driver, was before him, and had a limp little figure

in his arms, and was carrying it to the gaslight. John gave one look

and cried:</p>

<p>"It's the same kid, Bill! The one I told you of!"</p>

<p>True as truth were the ragged coat dangling from the pitiful

body, the little blue hands, 

<pb id="ep.gs.0007.10.jpg" n="88"/>

the thin shoulders, the stringy hair, the big arctics on the feet. And

in the road not far off was the curious chest of dark wood with iron

hasps.</p>

<p>"She ran under the car deliberate!" cried Bill. "I yelled to her,

but she looked at me and ran straight on!"</p>

<p>He was white in spite of his weather-beaten skin.</p>

<p>"I guess you wasn't drunk last night after all, John," said

he.</p>

<p>"You&#8212;you are sure the kid is&#8212;is there?" gasped John.</p>

<p>"Not so damned sure!" said Bill.</p>

<p>But a few minutes later it was taken away in a patrol wagon,

and with it the little box with iron hasps.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>