<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="stylesheet.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD peattie.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include/peattie.dtd" [

]>
<TEI id="ep.gs.0010">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Piano Next Door</title>
<title type="sub"></title>
<author n="Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935">Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935</author>
<principal>George-Bloomfield, Susanne, 1947-</principal>
<editor></editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Zach Bajaber</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Nebraska Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</publisher>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>ep.gs.0010</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<!-- <notesStmt>
<note></note>
</notesStmt> -->

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author n="Peattie, Elia W.">Elia W. Peattie</author>
<title level="m">The Shape of Fear and Other Ghostly Tales</title>
<title level="a">The Piano Next Door</title>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<publisher>Macmillan</publisher>
<date value="1898">1898</date>
<series>Short Story Index Reprint Series</series>
<pubPlace>Freeport, NY</pubPlace>
<publisher>Books for Libraries Press</publisher>
<date value="1969">1969</date>
<biblScope type="pages">115-126</biblScope>
</bibl>

</sourceDesc>

<!-- <notesStmt>
<note></note>
</notesStmt> -->
</fileDesc>


<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords n="genre">
<term>Short Story</term>
</keywords>
</textClass></profileDesc>


<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2009-02-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Vicki Martin</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Proofreading</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2008-11-17</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item></item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2007-10-31</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted from html</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>200y-mm-dd</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Transcribed by Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Original Transcription</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1>

<pb id="ep.gs.0010.01.jpg" n="115"/>

<head>THE PIANO NEXT DOOR</head>

<p>BABETTE had gone away for the summer; the furniture was in

its summer linens; the curtains were down, and Babette's husband,

John Boyce, was alone in the house. It was the first year of his

marriage, and he missed Babette. But then, as he often said to

himself, he ought never to have married her. He did it from pure

selfishness, and because he was determined to possess the most

illusive, tantalizing, elegant, and utterly unmoral little creature that

the sun shone upon. He wanted her because she reminded him of

birds, and flowers, and summer winds, and other exquisite things

created for the delectation of mankind. He neither expected nor

desired her to think. He had half-frightened her into 

<pb id="ep.gs.0010.02.jpg" n="116"/>

marrying him, had taken her to a poor man's home, provided her

with no society such as she had been accustomed to, and he had no

reasonable cause of complaint when she answered the call of

summer and flitted away, like a butterfly in the morning sunshine,

to the place where the flowers grew.</p>

<p>He wrote to her every evening, sitting in the stifling, ugly house,

and poured out his soul as if it were a libation to a goddess. She

sometimes answered by telegraph, sometimes by a perfumed note.

He schooled himself not to feel hurt. Why should Babette write?

Does a goldfinch indict epistles; or a humming-bird study

composition; or a glancing, red-scaled fish in summer shallows

consider the meaning of words?</p>

<p>He knew at the beginning what Babette was&#8212;guessed her

limitations&#8212;trembled when he buttoned her tiny glove&#8212;kissed her

dainty slipper when he found it in the closet after she was gone&#8212;

thrilled at the sound of her laugh, or the memory of it!  That was all. 

<pb id="ep.gs.0010.03.jpg" n="117"/>

A mere case of love.  He was in bonds. Babette was not.   Therefore

he was in the city, working overhours to pay for Babette's pretty

follies down at the seaside.  It was quite right and proper. He was a

grub in the furrow; she a lark in the blue. Those had always been

and always must be their relative positions.</p>

<p>Having attained a mood of philosophic calm, in which he was

prepared to spend his evenings alone&#8212;as became a grub&#8212;and to

await with dignified patience the return of his wife, it was in the

nature of an inconsistency that he should have walked the floor of

the dull little drawing-room like a lion in cage. It did not seem in

keeping with the position of superior serenity which he had

assumed, that, reading Babette's notes, he should have raged with

jealousy, or that, in the loneliness of his unkempt chamber, he

should have stretched out arms of longing. Even if Babette had been

present, she would only have smiled her gay little smile and co- 

<pb id="ep.gs.0010.04.jpg" n="118"/>

quetted with him. She could not understand. He had known, of

course, from the first moment, that she could not understand! And

so, why the ache, ache, ache of the heart! Or <hi rend="italic">was</hi> it the heart,

or the brain, or the soul?</p>

<p>Sometimes, when the evenings were so hot that he could not

endure the close air of the house, he sat on the narrow, dusty front

porch and looked about him at his neighbors. The street had once

been smart and aspiring, but it had fallen into decay and dejection.

Pale young men, with flurried-looking wives, seemed to Boyce to

occupy most of the houses. Sometimes three or four couples would

live in one house. Most of these appeared to be childless. The

women made a pretence at fashionable dressing, and wore their hair

elaborately in fashions which somehow suggested boarding-houses

to Boyce, though he could not have told why. Every house in the

block needed fresh paint. Lacking this renovation, the householders

tried to make up for it by 

<pb id="ep.gs.0010.05.jpg" n="119"/>

a display of lace curtains which, at every window, swayed in the

smoke-weighted breeze. Strips of carpeting were laid down the front

steps of the houses where the communities of young couples lived,

and here, evenings, the inmates of the houses gathered, committing

mild extravagances such as the treating of each other to ginger ale,

or beer, or ice-cream.</p>

<p>Boyce watched these tawdry makeshifts at sociability with

bitterness and loathing.   He wondered how he could have been such

a fool as to bring his exquisite Babette to this neighborhood.   How

could he expect that she would return to him? It was not reasonable.

He ought to go down on his knees with gratitude that she even

condescended to write him.</p>

<p>Sitting one night till late,&#8212;so late that the fashionable young

wives with their husbands had retired from the strips of stair

carpeting,&#8212;and raging at the loneliness which ate at his heart like a

cancer, he heard, softly creeping through the windows of the house

adjoin- 

<pb id="ep.gs.0010.06.jpg" n="120"/>

ing his own, the sound of comfortable melody.</p>

<p>It breathed upon his ear like a spirit of consolation, speaking of

peace, of love which needs no reward save its own sweetness, of

aspiration which looks forever beyond the thing of the hour to find

attainment in that which is eternal. So insidiously did it whisper

these things, so delicately did the simple and perfect melodies creep

upon the spirit&#8212;that Boyce felt no resentment, but from the first

listened as one who listens to learn, or as one who, fainting on the

hot road, hears, far in the ferny deeps below, the gurgle of a

spring.</p>

<p>Then came harmonies more intricate: fair fabrics of woven

sound, in the midst of which gleamed golden threads of joy; a

tapestry of sound, multi-tinted, gallant with story and achievement,

and beautiful things.   Boyce, sitting on his absurd piazza, with his

knees jambed against the balustrade, and his chair back against the

dun-colored wall of his house, seemed to be walking in the

cathedral 

<pb id="ep.gs.0010.07.jpg" n="121"/>

of the redwood forest, with blue above him, a vast hymn in his ears,

pungent perfume in his nostrils, and mighty shafts of trees lifting

themselves to heaven, proud and erect as pure men before their

Judge. He stood on a mountain at sunrise, and saw the marvels of

the amethystine clouds below his feet, heard an eternal and white

silence, such as broods among the everlasting snows, and saw an

eagle winging for the sun.  He was in a city, and away from him,

diverging like the spokes of a wheel, ran thronging streets, and to

his sense came the beat, beat, beat of the city's heart. He saw the

golden alchemy of a chosen race; saw greed transmitted to progress;

saw that which had enslaved men, work at last to their liberation;

heard the roar of mighty mills, and on the streets all the peoples of

earth walking with common purposes, in fealty and understanding.

And then, from the swelling of this concourse of great sounds, came

a diminuendo, calm as philosophy, and from that, nothingness.</p>

<pb id="ep.gs.0010.08.jpg" n="122"/>

<p>Boyce sat still for a long time, listening to the echoes which this

music had awakened in his soul. He retired, at length, content, but

determined that upon the morrow he would watch&#8212;the day being

Sunday&#8212;for the musician who had so moved and taught him.</p>

<p>He arose early, therefore, and having prepared his own simple

breakfast of fruit and coffee, took his station by the window to

watch for the man. For he felt convinced that the exposition he had

heard was that of a masculine mind. The long, hot hours of the

morning went by, but the front door of the house next to his did not

open.</p>

<p>"These artists sleep late," he complained. Still he watched. He

was too much afraid of losing him to go out for dinner. By three 

in the afternoon he had grown impatient. He went to the house next

door and rang the bell.   There was no response.   He thundered

another appeal.  An old woman with a cloth about her head

answered the door. 

<pb id="ep.gs.0010.09.jpg" n="123"/>

She was very deaf, and Boyce had difficulty in making himself

understood.</p>

<p>"The family is in the country," was all she would say. "The

family will not be home till September."</p>

<p>"But there is some one living here?" shouted Boyce.</p>

<p>"<hi rend="italic">I</hi> live here," she said with dignity, putting back a wisp

of dirty gray hair behind her ear. "It is my house. I sublet to the

family."</p>

<p>"What family?"</p>

<p>But the old creature was not communicative.</p>

<p>"The family that lives here," she said.</p>

<p>"Then who plays the piano in this house?" roared Boyce. "Do

you?"</p>

<p>He thought a shade of pallor showed itself on her ash-colored

cheeks. Yet she smiled a little at the idea of her playing.</p>

<p>"There is no piano," she said, and she put an enigmatical

emphasis to the words.</p>

<p>"Nonsense," cried Boyce, indignantly. "I 

<pb id="ep.gs.0010.10.jpg" n="124"/>

heard a piano being played in this very house

for hours last night!"</p>

<p>"You may enter," said the old woman, with an accent more

vicious than hospitable.</p>

<p>Boyce almost burst into the drawing-room. It was a dusty and

forbidding place, with ugly furniture and gaudy walls. No piano nor

any other musical instrument stood in it. The intruder turned an

angry and baffled face to the old woman, who was smiling with

ill-concealed exultation.</p>

<p>"I shall see the other rooms," he announced. The old woman did

not appear to be surprised at his impertinence.</p>

<p>"As you please," she said.</p>

<p>So, with the hobbling creature, with her bandaged head, for a

guide, he explored every room of the house, which being identical

with his own, he could do without fear of leaving any apartment

unentered. But no piano did he find!</p>

<p>"Explain," roared Boyce at length, turning upon the leering old

hag beside him. "Ex-

<pb id="ep.gs.0010.11.jpg" n="125"/>

plain! For surely I heard music more beautiful than I can tell."</p>

<p>"I know nothing," she said. "But it is true I once had a lodger

who rented the front room, and that he played upon the piano. I am

poor at hearing, but he must have played well, for all the neighbors

used to come in front of the house to listen, and sometimes they

applauded him, and sometimes they were still.   I could tell by

watching their hands. Sometimes little children came and danced.

Other times young men and women came and listened. But the

young man died. The neighbors were angry. They came to look at

him and said he had starved to death.  It was no fault of mine. I sold

his piano to pay his funeral expenses&#8212;and it took every cent to pay

for them too, I'd have you know.   But since then, sometimes&#8212;still,

it must be nonsense, for I never heard it&#8212;folks say that he plays the

piano in my room. It has kept me out of the letting of it more than

once. But 

<pb id="ep.gs.0010.12.jpg" n="126"/>

the family doesn't seem to mind&#8212;the family that lives here, you

know. They will be back in September. Yes."</p>

<p>Boyce left her nodding her thanks at what he had placed in her

hand, and went home to write it all to Babette&#8212;Babette who would

laugh so merrily when she read it!</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>