<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="stylesheet.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD peattie.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include/peattie.dtd" []><TEI id="ep.ss.0027"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">Rubaiyat and the Liner</title><title type="sub"></title><author n="Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935">Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935</author><principal>George-Bloomfield, Susanne, 1947-</principal><editor></editor><respStmt><resp>Project Team</resp><name>Zach Bajaber</name><name>Nicholas Swiercek</name><name>Laura Weakly</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2009</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Nebraska Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</publisher><pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> <address><addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address><idno>ep.ss.0027</idno><availability><p></p></availability></publicationStmt><!-- <notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt> --><sourceDesc><bibl><author n="Peattie, Elia W.">Elia W. Peattie</author><title level="a">"The Rubaiyat and the Liner"</title><title level="m">Quaint Courtships: Harper's Novelettes</title><editor>Ed. William Dean Howells and Henry Mills Alden</editor><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers</publisher><date value="1906">1906</date><biblScope type="pages">233&#8211;255</biblScope></bibl></sourceDesc><!-- <notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt> --></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords n="genre"><term>Short Story</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><!-- <encodingDesc><editorialDecl><correction><p></p></correction><normalization><p></p></normalization></editorialDecl></encodingDesc> --><revisionDesc><change><date>2007-10-30</date><respStmt><name>Laura Weakly</name></respStmt><item>Converted from html</item></change><change><date>200y-mm-dd</date><respStmt><name>Transcribed by Judy Boss</name></respStmt><item>Original Transcription</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1><pb id="ep.ss.0027.01.jpg" n="233"/><head>The Rubaiyat and the Liner</head><byline>ELIA W. PEATTIE</byline><p>"CHUG-CHUG, chug-chug!"</p><p>That was the liner, and it had been saying the same thing for twonights and two days. Therefore nobody paid any attention to it &#8212;except Chalmers Payne, the moodiest of the passengers, whonoticed it and said to himself that, for his part, it did as well as anyother sound, and was much better than most persons' conversation.</p><p>It will be guessed that Mr. Chalmers Payne was in an irritableframe of mind. He was even retaliative, and to the liner's continuediteration of its innocent remark he retorted in the words of oldOmar:<quote>"Perplext no more with Human or Divine,<lb/>&#160;To-morrow's tangle to the winds resign,<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;And lose your fingers in the tresses of<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;The cypress-slender Minister of Wine.<lb/><lb/>"And if the wine you drink, the Lip you press,<lb/>&#160;End in what All begins and ends in &#8212; Yes;<lb/><milestone unit="horbar" /><pb id="ep.ss.0027.02.jpg" n="234"/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Think then you are To-day what Yes-<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;terday<lb/>&#160;You were &#8212; To-morrow you shall not be less.<lb/><lb/>"So when the Angel of the Darker Drink<lb/>&#160;At last shall find you by the River-brink,<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;And, offering his Cup, invite your Soul<lb/>&#160;Forth to your Lips to quaff &#8212; you shall not<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;shrink."</quote></p><p>To these melancholy mutterings, the liner, insouciant, and notcaring a peg for any philosophy &#8212; save that of the open road &#8212;shouldered along through jewel-green waves, and remarked,"Chug-chug, chug-chug!"</p><p>Mr. Payne was inclined to quarrel with the Tent-Maker on onescore only. He did not think that he was to-day what he wasyesterday. Yesterday &#8212; figuratively speaking &#8212; he had hope. He wasconscious of his youth. A fine, buoyant egotism sustained him, andhe believed that he was about to be crowned with a beautiful joy.</p><p>He had sauntered up to his joy, so to speak, cocksure, hands inpockets, and as he smiled with easy assurance, behold the joyturned into a sorrow. The face of the dryad smiling through theyoung grape leaves was that of a withered hag, and the leaves of thevine were dead and flapped on sapless stems!</p><pb id="ep.ss.0027.03.jpg" n="235"/><p>Well, well, there was always a sorry fatalism to comfort one injoy's despite.</p><quote>"Then to the rolling Heav'n itself, I cried,<lb/>&#160;Asking, 'What Lamp had Destiny to guide<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Her little Children stumbling in the<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Dark?'"</quote><p>The answer was old as patience &#8212; as old as courage. But totheorize about it was really superfluous! Why think at all? Why notsay chug-chug like the liner?</p><quote>"We are no other than a moving row<lb/>&#160;Of Magic Shadow-shapes that come and<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;go &#8212;"</quote><p>Dinner! Was it possible? The day had been a blur! Well,probably all the rest of life would be a blur. Anyway, one could stilldine, and he recollected that the pur&#233;e of tomatoes at lastnight's dinner had been rather to his liking. He seated himselfdeliberately at the board, congratulating himself that he would beallowed to go through the duty of eating without interruption. Theplace at his right had been vacant ever since they left Southampton.At his left was a gentleman of uncertain hearing and a bullet-prooffrown.</p><p>As the seat at his right had been <orig reg="vacant">va-<pb id="ep.ss.0027.04.jpg" n="236"/>cant</orig> so long, he took the liberty of laying in it his gloves, hissea-glass, a book with uncut leaves, and a crimson silk neck-scarf.</p><p>"I beg your pardon," said the waiter, "but the lady who is to sithere is coming, sir."</p><p>"The devil she is!" thought Payne. "Will the creature expect meto talk? Will she require me to look after her in the matter of pepperand salt? Why couldn't I have been left in peace?"</p><p>He gathered up his possessions, and arose gravely with anautomatic courtesy, and lifted eyes with a wooden expression tostare at the intruder.</p><p>He faced the one person in the world whom it was most of painand happiness to meet &#8212; the woman between whom and himself hemeant to put a good half of the round world; and he read in hertroubled gray eyes the confession that if there was anything oranybody from which she would willingly have been protected it washe &#8212; Chalmers Payne.</p><p>Conscious of their neighbors, they bowed. Payne saw hercomfortably seated. He sat down and slowly emptied his glass ofice-water.  He preserved his wooden expression of countenance andturned towards her.</p><pb id="ep.ss.0027.05.jpg" n="237"/><p>"The old man on my right is deaf," he said.</p><p>"So am I," she retorted.</p><p>"Not so deaf, I hope, that you won't hear me explain that I had nomore notion of your being on this ship than of Sappho being here!"</p><p>"You refer to &#8212; the Greek Sappho, Mr. Payne?"</p><p>"Assuredly. You told me &#8212; 'fore Heaven, why are women soinconsistent? &#8212; you told me you were going anywhere rather than toAmerica &#8212; that you were at the beginning of your journeyings &#8212;that you had an engagement with some Mahatmas on the top of theHimal &#8212;"</p><p>"And you &#8212; you were going to South Africa."</p><p>"I said nothing of the sort. I &#8212;" </p><p>"Well, I couldn't go about another day. No matter whether I wasconsistent or inconsistent! I was worn out and ill. I've been seeingtoo much &#8212;"</p><p>"You told me you could never see enough!"</p><p>"Well, never mind all that. I acted impulsively, I confess.  Myaunt was shocked. She thought I was ungrateful &#8212; particularly whenI openly rejoiced that she was not able to find a chaperon for me."</p><pb id="ep.ss.0027.06.jpg" n="238"/><p>"It's none of my business, anyway. I was stupid to show mysurprise. I ought never to be surprised at anything you do, I knowthat. As for me, I'm tired of imitating the Wandering Jew. Besides,my father's old partner &#8212; mine he is now, I suppose, though I can'tget used to that idea &#8212; wants me to come home. He says I'm needed.So I'm rolling up my sleeves, figuratively speaking. But I shouldcertainly have delayed my journey if I had guessed you were to beon this boat."</p><p>"It's very annoying altogether," she said, with open vexation. "Itlooks so silly! What will my aunt say?"</p><p>"I don't think she'll say anything. You are on an Atlantic liner,with nine hundred and ninety-nine souls who are nothing to you,and one who is less than nothing. I believe that was the expressionyou used the other day &#8212; less than nothing?"</p><p>The girl's delicate face flushed hotly.</p><p>"I'm not so strong," she murmured. " It's true that I am worn out,and my voyage has done nothing so far towards restoring me. Onthe contrary, I have been suffering. I fainted again and againyesterday, and it took a great deal of courage for me to venture outto-day.<pb id="ep.ss.0027.07.jpg" n="239"/>So you must be merciful for a little while. Your enemy is down, yousee."</p><p>"My enemy!" He gave the words an accent at once bitter andhumorous. "I'll not say another personal word," he murmured,contritely. "Tell me if you feel faint at any moment, and let me helpyou. Please treat me as if I were your &#8212; your uncle!"</p><p>She smiled faintly.</p><p>"You are asking a great deal," she couldn't help saying,somewhat coquettishly, and then he remembered how he had seenher hanging about her uncle's neck, and he flushed too.</p><p>There was quite a long silence. She picked at her food delicately,and Payne suggested some claret. Her face showed that she wouldhave preferred not to accept any favor from him, no matter howtrifling, hut she evidently considered it puerile to refuse.</p><p>"It <hi rend="italic">is</hi> mighty awkward for you!" he burst out, suddenly,"my being here. I suppose you actually find it hard to believe that itwas an accident &#8212;"</p><p>"I haven't the least occasion to doubt your word, Mr. Payne.Have I ever done anything to make you suppose that I didn't respectyou?"</p><p>"Oh, I didn't mean that! Heavens!<pb id="ep.ss.0027.08.jpg" n="240"/>what a cad you must think me! I have a faculty for being stupidwhen you are around, you know. It's my misfortune. But &#8212; beholdmy generosity! &#8212; I shall have a talk with the purser, Miss Curtis,and get him to change my place for me. Some good-natured personwill consent to make the alteration."</p><p>"You mean you will put some one else here in your place besideme?"</p><p>"It's the least I can do, isn't it? Now, whom would you suggest? Pick out somebody. There's that motherly-looking German woman,over there. She's a baroness &#8212;"</p><p>"She?  She'll tell me twice every meal that American girls are notbrought up with a knowledge of cooking. She will tell me how shehas met them at Kaffeeklatsches, and how they confessed that theydidn't cook! No, no; you must try another one!"</p><p>"Well, if you object to her, there's that quiet gentleman who iseating his ice with the aid of two pairs of spectacles. Thatgentleman is a specialist in bacilli. He has little steel-bound bottlesin his room which, if you were to break them among this ship-loadof passengers, would depopulate the ship. I think he is taking homethe bacilli of the bubonic<pb id="ep.ss.0027.09.jpg" n="241"/>plague as a present to our country. Remember, if you got on theright side of him, that you would have a vengeance beyond thedreams of the Borgias at your command!"</p><p>"Oh, the terrible creature! Mr. Payne, how could you mentionhim? What if he were to take me for a guinea-pig or a rabbit? No, Iprefer the English-looking mummy over there."</p><p>"Who? Miss Hull? She's not half bad. She's a great traveller. Shehas been almost everywhere, and is now hastening to make iteverywhere. She carries her own tea with her, and steeps it at fiveexactly every afternoon. She tells me that once, being shipwrecked,she grasped her tea-caddy, her alcohol-stove, and a large bottle ofalcohol, and prepared for the worst. They drifted four days on a raft,and she made five-o'clock tea every day, to the great encouragementof the unfortunates. Miss Hull is an English spinster, who has afortune and no household, and who is going about to see how otherfolks keep house &#8212; FeeJee-Islanders, and Tagals, and Kafirs. Shelikes them all, I believe. Indeed, she says she likes everything &#8212;except the snug English village where she was brought up.  She saysthat when she<pb id="ep.ss.0027.10.jpg" n="242"/>lived there she did exactly the same thing between sunup andsundown for eight years. For example, she had the curate to teaevery Wednesday evening during that entire time, and whenpossible she had periwinkles."</p><p>"And nothing came of it?"</p><p>"Oh yes, an enormous consumption of tea-biscuits &#8212; nothingmore. Then it occurred to her to travel. So she went to the nextshire, and liked it so well that she plunged off to London, then to theHebrides. After that there was no stopping her. She likes the islandsbetter than the continents, and is collecting hats made of sea-grass.She already has five hundred and forty-two varieties. Really, youwould not find her half so bad."</p><p>Helen Curtis finished her coffee, and laid her napkin, beside herplate.</p><p>"Oh, if it comes to the negative virtues, you haven't been sodisagreeable yourself to-day as you might have been. I'm underobligations to you. It <hi rend="italic">was</hi> rather nice to meet an oldacquaintance."</p><p>The tone was formal, and put Payne ten thousand leagues awayfrom her.</p><p>"Thank you," he said, with mock gratitude. "<hi rend="italic">I'm</hi> underobligations for<pb id="ep.ss.0027.11.jpg" n="243"/>your courtesy, madam."  She dropped her handkerchief as she arose,and he picked up the trifle and gave it to her. Their fingers met, andhe withdrew his hand with a quick gesture.</p><p>"You must allow me to see you safely to your room," he urged."Or else to your deck chair."</p><p>"Thank you. I'll go on deck, I think, and you may call the boy togo for my rug."</p><p>He put her on the lee side, and wrapped her in a McCallum plaid,and brought her some magazines from his own stateroom.  Then hestood erect and saluted.</p><p>"Madam, have I the honor to be dismissed?"</p><p>She looked up and gave a friendly smile in spite of herself.</p><p>"You are very good," she said. "I am always remembering thatyou are good, and the thought annoys me."</p><p>"Oh, it needn't," he responded, in a philosophic tone, looking offtowards the jagged line of the horizon, where the purple wavesshowed their changing outline. "If you are wondering why it is thatyou dislike me when you find nothing of which to disapprove in myconduct, don't let that puzzle you any long-<pb id="ep.ss.0027.12.jpg" n="244"/>er. Regard does not depend upon character.  The mystery ofattraction has never been solved.   Now, I've seen women morebeautiful than you; I know many who are more learned; as for asense of justice and fairness, why, I don't think you understand thefirst principles. Yet you are the one woman in the world for me.Now that you've taken love out of my life, this world is nothingmore to me than a workshop. I shall get up every morning and putmyself at my bench, so to speak, and work till nightfall. Then I shallsleep. It is dull, but it doesn't matter. I have been at some trouble toconvince myself of the fact that it doesn't matter, and I value theconviction. Life isn't as disheartening as it would be if it lastedlonger.</p><quote>"'Tis but a Tent where takes his one day's<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;rest<lb/>&#160;A Sultan to the realms of Death addrest;<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;The Sultan rises, and the dark Ferrash<lb/>&#160;Strikes, and prepares it for another guest."</quote><p>Miss Curtis sat up in her chair, and her eyes were flashingindignation.</p><p>"I won't listen in silence to the profanity of that old heathen," shecried.</p><p>"You refer to my friend Omar?" <orig reg="inquired">in-<pb id="ep.ss.0027.13.jpg" n="245"/>quired</orig> Payne, quizzically, dropping his earnestness as soon as sheassumed it.</p><p>"I consider him one of the most dangerous of men! Once youwould have been above advancing such philosophy! The idea ofyour talking that inert fatalism! It's incredible that you shouldadmire what is supine and cowardly &#8212;"</p><p>Payne's eyes were twinkling. He lit his pipe with a "By yourpermission," and between the puffs chanted:</p><quote>"Ah, Love! could thou and I with Fate<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;conspire<lb/>&#160;To grasp this sorry scheme of Things<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;entire<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Would we not shatter it to bits &#8212; and<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;then<lb/>&#160;Remould it nearer to the Heart's Desire!"</quote><p>"Even that is blasphemous impertinence!" the lady protested,knowing that she was angry, and rejoicing in the sensation.</p><p>"You think so?" cried Payne, not waiting for her to finish. "Whydid you complain, then, of taking up the burden of common things?Do you want to be reminded of what you told me? You said that theroving life you had been leading in Europe for the past two yearshad unsettled you. You said you wanted<pb id="ep.ss.0027.14.jpg" n="246"/>to live among the old things and the dreams of old things. You likedthe sense of irresponsible delight, and weren't prepared to say thatyou could ever assume the dull domestic round in a commonplacetown. You considered the love of one human creature altogether toosmall and banal a thing to make you forego your intellectualincursions into the lands of delight. You were of the opinion thatyou loved many thousand creatures, most of them dead, and toenjoy their society to the full it was necessary for you to look at thecathedrals they had builded, to read the books they had written, orgaze upon the canvases they had painted. You were in a poppy sleepon the mystic flowers of ancient dreams. Wasn't that it? So I, a merepractical, every-day fellow, who had shown an unaccountableweakness in staying away from home a full year longer than I hadany business to, was to go back alone to my work and my emptyhouse, and console myself with the day's work. You were to gowalking along the twilight path where the half-gods had walkedbefore you, and I was to trudge up a dusty road fringed with pusley,and ending in a summer kitchen. Isn't that about it?"</p><pb id="ep.ss.0027.15.jpg" n="247"/><p>She spread out the folds of her gown and looked down at them ina somewhat embarrassed manner, seemingly submerged by thisflood of protesting eloquence.</p><p>"You were afraid to look anything in the face," he went on, notgiving her time to recover her breath.   "You thought you could livein a world of beauty and never have any hard work. I suppose if youhad seen the gardener wiping the sweat off his brow you would nothave picked any of the roses in that garden at Lucerne. I supposenot! Well, let me assure you of one thing &#8212; there'scommonplaceness everywhere. Probably some one had to washthose white dresses Sappho used to wear when she sat beside thesea. Maybe Sappho did them up herself, eh?"</p><p>He stopped and gave way to his bathos, throwing back his headand laughing heartily.</p><p>"Well, well, I'm through with railing at you. But I left you eatinglotus, hollow-eyed and steeped in dreams. You were listening to thesurf on Calypso's Isle.  I was hearing nothing but the sound of yourvoice. Now I've stumbled on a soporific philosophy, and am gettingall I can out of the an&#230;sthesia, and you<pb id="ep.ss.0027.16.jpg" n="248"/>are reproaching me. It's like your inconsistency, isn't it?"</p><p>She put up one hand to stop him, but he went on, recurring oncemore to the poet:</p><quote>"The Worldly Hope men set their Hearts<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;upon<lb/>&#160;Turns Ashes &#8212; or it prospers; and anon,<lb/>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Like snow upon the Desert's dusty Face<lb/>&#160;Lighting a little Hour or two, is gone."</quote><p>She tried to speak, but he lifted his hat and left her, and going tothe other side of the deck, paced up and down there swiftly, andthought of a number of things. For one thing, he reflected howludicrous was life! Here was Helen Curtis, fleeing from therecollection of him; here was himself, fleeing from the too-sweetactuality of her calm face and lambent eyes; and they were set downface to face in midocean! Such a preposterous trick on the part ofthe Three!</p><p>"I suppose happiness is never anything more than a mirage," hesaid to himself as he paced. "It is bright at times and then dim, andat present, for me, it is inverted. The business of the traveller,however, is to tramp on in the sun and the sand, with an eye to thecompass and giving no heed to evanishing<pb id="ep.ss.0027.17.jpg" n="249"/>gleams of fairy lakes and plumelike palms. Tramping on in the sandisn't as bad as it might be, either, when one gets used to it. Thesimoon is on me now, but I'll weather it. I've <hi rend="italic">got</hi> to. I<hi rend="italic">won't be</hi> downed!"</p><p>He put his head up and tried to think he was courageous. Thegloom of the night was about him now, and the strange voices of thesea called one to the other. He tried to turn his thought to practicalthings. He would go home to the vacant old house where he hadbeen born; he would make it livable, let the sunshine into it,modernize it to an extent, and then get some one under its roof.While there were so many homeless folk in the world it wasn't rightto have an untenanted house. Then he'd get down to business, goodand hard, and bring the thing up. It was a good business, and it hadan honorable reputation. He had been too unappreciative of this finelegacy. Well, there were excuses. At school he had thought of otherthings &#8212; and the life of the fraternity house had been a gallant one!  Then came his wander year &#8212; which stretched into two.  And now,having eaten of the apples of Paradise and felt them turn tobitterness in his mouth, he would go back to duty.</p><pb id="ep.ss.0027.18.jpg" n="250"/><p>He wished he had never seen her again &#8212; after that night whenshe belied her long-continued kindness to him with her indifferentrejection of his devotion. He devoutly wished he had not beenforced to feel again the subtle fascination of those deep eyes, andhear the thrilling contralto of that rich voice! She was unscrupulousin her cold selfishness &#8212;</p><p>A sudden, inexplicable trembling of the whole great ship! Afrightened quivering, a lurch, a crash!</p><p>The chug-chug ceased. No &#8212; it couldn't! Nothing like that everhappened to a ship of the line on a comparatively quiet night! Ofcourse not!</p><p>Of course not &#8212; but for all of that, they were as inert as a raft,and the passengers were beginning to skurry about and to ask thethird officer and the fourth officer what t' dickens it meant. Thethird officer and the fourth officer did not know, but felt convinced&#8212; professionally convinced &#8212; that it was nothing. The firstengineer? He had gone below. Oh, it was nothing.   The captain? Really, they could not say where he was.</p><p>Chalmers Payne strode around the after-cabin, and then ran tothe spot where he had left Helen Curtis. She<pb id="ep.ss.0027.19.jpg" n="251"/>was still there. She sat up and put both her hands in his.</p><p>"I knew you'd be here as soon as you could, so I didn't move! Ididn't want to put you to the trouble to look for me!"</p><p>He held her hands hard.</p><p>"I don't think it is much of anything," he said. "It can't be. There'sno smell of fire. The sea is not heavy. At the very worst &#8212;"</p><p>"Be sure, won't you, that we're not separated? One of us might beput in one boat and one in another, you know, if it should really be&#8212; be fire or something. Then, if a storm came up and &#8212;"</p><p>People were running with vague rumors.  They called out thisand that alarm. It was possible to feel the panic gathering.</p><p>"Remember," Helen Curtis whispered, "whatever comes, that webelong together."</p><p>"We do!" he acquiesced, saying the words between his teeth. "Ihave known it a long time. But you &#8212;"</p><p>"Oh, so have I! But what made you so sure? What was thereabout your home and your work and yourself to make you soperfectly sure I would be interested in them all my life? You didn'tlay out any scheme for me at all,<pb id="ep.ss.0027.20.jpg" n="252"/>or act as if you thought I had any dreams or aspirations. I was tocome and observe you become distinguished &#8212; I was to watch whatyou could do! Oh, Chalmers, I was willing, but what made you sosure?"</p><p>"Then you loved me? You loved me?" She looked white andscared, and he could feel her hands chill and tremble.</p><p>"How ready you are to use that word! I'm afraid of it.  I alwayssaid I wouldn't speak it till I <hi rend="italic">had</hi> to.  It frightens me &#8212; itmeans so much. If I said it to you I could never say it to any oneelse, no matter how &#8212;"</p><p>"Not on any account! Say it, Helen!"</p><p>"I wish to explain. I &#8212; I couldn't stand the aimlessness of lifeafter you left. I began to suspect that it was you who madeeverything so interesting. I wasn't so enamoured with the ancientsas I thought I was; but I was enamoured with your contemplation ofmy pose. Oh, I've been dissecting myself! Should I really have caredso much for Lucerne and Nuremberg if you hadn't been with me? Iconcluded that I should not. Well, said I to myself, if he can makethe Old World so fascinating, can he not do something for the NewWorld, too?"</p><p>An alarmist rushed by.</p><pb id="ep.ss.0027.21.jpg" n="253"/><p>"They are going to lower the boats!" he cried.  "Better get yourvaluables together."</p><p>"There's a panic in the steerage," another cried.</p><p>"Oh, Helen! Go on. Don't let anything interrupt you."</p><p>"I won't. I realize that you ought to be told that I love you. I do. Ilove you. I'm twenty-three, and I never said the words to any oneelse, even though I'm an American girl. And I'll never speak them toany one but you. I'm sure of it now. But I wouldn't say it till I wasquite, quite sure."</p><p>The captain came pacing down the deck leisurely. He lifted hishat as he passed Payne and Miss Curtis.</p><p>"We shall be on our way in a few minutes," he said, agreeably. "Ihope this young lady has not suffered any alarm."</p><p>Helen showed him a face on which anything was written ratherthan fear.</p><p>"The port shaft broke off somewhere near the truss-block at themouth of the sleeve of the shaft, and the outer end of the shaft andthe propeller dropped to the bottom of the sea. It's quiteinexplicable, but I find in my experience that inexplicable thingsfrequently happen.<pb id="ep.ss.0027.22.jpg" n="254"/>We shall finish our run with the starboard shaft only, and shall heobliged to reduce our speed to an average of three hundred and sixtyknots daily."</p><p>He repeated this in a voice of impersonal courtesy, and went onto the next group. Helen Curtis settled back in her chair and smiledup at her lover.</p><p>"We shall be at sea at least two days longer," he said, exultantly.</p><p>"Ah, what shall we do to pass the time?" she interrupted, withmocking coquetry.</p><p>"Chug-chug, chug-chug!"</p><p>It was the liner.</p><quote>"Ah, my Beloved, fill the Cup that clears<lb/>&#160;To-day of past Regret and future Fears &#8212;"</quote><p>This was Omar, but Miss Curtis would not listen.</p><p>"I've an aversion to your eloquent old heathen," she pleaded."You must not quote him, really."</p><p>"If you insist, I'll refrain. Can't I even quote 'A book of versesunderneath the bough &#8212;'"</p><p>"Oh, not on any account! That least of all."</p><p>"You don't want me to be hackneyed? Well, I'll be perfectlyoriginal. I know<pb id="ep.ss.0027.23.jpg" n="255"/>one thing I can say which will always sound mysterious andmarvellous!"</p><p>"Say it, say it!" she commanded, imperiously, knowing quitewell what it was.</p><p>So he said it, and the two sat and looked off across the darkenedwater and at the pale, reluctant stars, beholding, for that night atleast, the passionate inner sense of the universe. They said nothingmore.</p><p>But as for the liner, it continued with its emphatic reiteration.</p></div1></body></text></TEI>