<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="stylesheet.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD peattie.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include/peattie.dtd" []><TEI id="ep.ss.0028"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Stage Coach</title><title type="sub"></title><author n="Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935">Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935</author><principal>George-Bloomfield, Susanne, 1947-</principal><editor></editor><respStmt><resp>Project Team</resp><name>Zach Bajaber</name><name>Nicholas Swiercek</name><name>Laura Weakly</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2009</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Nebraska Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</publisher><pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> <address><addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address><idno>ep.ss.0028</idno><availability><p></p></availability></publicationStmt><!-- <notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt> --><sourceDesc><bibl><author n="Peattie, Elia W.">Elia W. Peattie</author><title level="a">"The Stage Coach"</title><title level="j">Atlantic Monthly</title><biblScope type="volume">93</biblScope><date value="1904-05">May 1904</date><biblScope type="pages">787&#8211;796</biblScope></bibl></sourceDesc><!-- <notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt> --></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><correction><p></p></correction><normalization><p>Note: I have closed contractions; e.g., "do n't" has become "don't" etc.</p></normalization></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords n="genre"><term>Short Story</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2007-10-30</date><respStmt><name>Laura Weakly</name></respStmt><item>Converted from html</item></change><change><date>200y-mm-dd</date><respStmt><name>Transcribed by Judy Boss</name></respStmt><item>Original Transcription</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1><pb id="ep.ss.0028.01.jpg" n="787"/><head>THE STAGE COACH</head><p>At the very threshold of life Julian Grabo met with anObstacle.  It filled the doorway.  He could not pass nor see beyondit.</p><p>"By Jove, what a nuisance!" he had cried when the doctor toldhim he had not more than six months to live.</p><p>"But perhaps," said the physician, "if you'll go into the aridcountry, you'll make the six months into a year."</p><p>"I could put in a year excellently," mused Grabo.  "I believe I'llgo."</p><p>He could hardly realize that he was in danger.  He did not feeldepleted nor weakened.  He was full of excitable life, and interestedin everything,&#8211;men, women, animals, poetry, history, andpossibilities.</p><p>"You could put me anywhere and I'd amuse myself," he said toa friend.  "I never yet complained about anything,&#8211;not even mycoffee.  It seems such a waste of good nature for ME to go off!"</p><p>His friends were incredulous,&#8211;the men swore and the womenwept.  But Grabo, who had once bellowed like a calf when hisfootball team had been beaten by a rival college, now shed no tear. He sent out his farewell cards, packed up his portable possessions,and set off post haste for a sheep ranch in Colorado, which was keptby a young Englishman he had met on his travels.</p><p>On the cars he tried to think things over, but his mind wouldnot concentrate.  All he could think of was Stevenson's epitaph,which the rails rattled off at a brisk tempo: &#8211;</p><quote><lg><l>Under the wide and starry sky,</l><l>Dig the grave and let me lie.</l><l>Glad did I live and gladly die,</l><l rend="indented">And I laid me down with a will.</l></lg><lg><l>This be the verse you grave for me:</l><l>Here he lies where he longed to be;</l><l>Home is the sailor, home from the sea,</l><l rend="indented">And the hunter home from the hill.</l></lg></quote><p>"But the real trouble with all that is," he said to the rails, "thatthis hunter has not yet been to the hill, nor this sailor to the sea."</p><p>The rails kept up an idiot-iteration, however: &#8211;<quote><lg><l rend="indented">Glad did I live and gladly die.</l><l rend="indented">Glad did I live and gladly die!</l></lg></quote></p><p>He grew more and more dejected as he went westward.  Heresented the vigor of the engineer who stuck his grimy face out ofthe cab to nod to Grabo as he paced the platform; he was angry withthe brunette young woman who was on her way to Los Angeles andexpected to find it gay; he detested the hale old man who toldstories in the smoking compartment.  He grew bitter at theinequalities of fate.  By degrees he reached despair, then abjection. He sank into a sodden reverie, forgot to eat, slept as if he weredrugged, and awoke with a semi-prostration upon him.  This madehim exaggerate his symptoms.</p><p>"It will not be even three months," his frightened spiritshrieked out to his trembling body.</p><p>At Upper Mesa he was to take a stage coach, and he loathedthe idea, for it meant that he was to have companions.  And, trulyenough, he found himself in intimate proximity to them.  He wouldhave liked to shut them out of his consciousness, but so far frombeing able to do that, he was forced into a minute yet distastefulobservation of them.</p><p>As a man doomed to die before sundown will watch theprogress of a fly on the wall, or count the tiles on the floor of hiscell, so Julian observed his companions, though they were to him asnegligible as tiles or flies.</p><p>There were five passengers within the coach and one outsidewith the driver.  To begin with, there was Grabo, the doomed andunreconciled.  Then there<pb id="ep.ss.0028.02.jpg" n="788"/>was an old man, a woman of forty, a woman of seventy-five, and achild&#8211;a girl&#8211;of seven.  Outside were Tuttle Underwood, a miner,and Henry Victor, the owner and driver of the stage coach.  Thesetwo men had introduced themselves to Grabo.  Victor measured sixfeet three, and he handled the ribbons of his four-in-hand withhappy nonchalance.  The Rockies have a breed of their own, andVictor was a Rocky Mountain man.  His hands, face, and beardwere the color of well-seasoned sandstone, and he affected the samecolor in his clothes.  Never did a human being fit moreunobtrusively into a landscape.  His voice had an agreeablemonotone which accorded with the minor, undulating harmonies ofwind, water, and trees which soughed in the ca&#241;ons.  If someover-musician, reflected Grabo, could find the keynote to theRockies, that would be the keynote to Henry Victor, too.</p><p>As for his four bays, they were mountain horses as surely astheir driver was a mountain man, and no one of them was renderedin the least nervous by the fact that the rear wheels of the coachwere flirting over the precipice as the vehicle flung around thebuttressed rock.</p><p>Underwood, the miner, was as lean as a coyote.  His iron-grayhair was shaggy, his eyes in perfect focus, his hand good for theexigeant shot.  He wore a dust-colored hat, a blue flannel shirt, afaded coat, trousers of the same sad fabric tucked in handsomeboots, and he was belted and armed.  He looked to Grabo as if hewould probably live forever.</p><p>As for the people within the coach, each one was alone.  Nonehad known any other member of the company till that hour.  Eventhe child was alone, her only companion being an ugly doll.</p><p>"You are my little girl," she was heard to babble.  "Really andtruly you are, though I haven't seen you since ever.  You've beenliving away off with your grandmother for years 'n' years, and nowyou're coming home to your own mamma.  You'd better look nice,or she won't like you, so there!"</p><p>She found a bit of string in the bottom of the coach and tied itaround the doll's neck.</p><p>"There!" she said in satisfied accents, "now you've got a tagon, telling just who you are and where you're going, and therewouldn't be any sense in your getting lost.  You just go up toanybody, man <hi rend="italic">or</hi> woman, and show 'em that tag, and they'llhelp you on.  Folks is always good to a child."</p><p>This optimistic remark was followed by a sigh on the part ofthe child, and seemed to be more of a creed than a conviction.  Itcreated a mild sensation.  The old man looked appealingly at thewomen.  The old woman felt in her bag for treasures which she didnot find.  The woman of forty started up from a reverie, regardedthe child in a puzzled and somewhat embarrassed fashion, and thenseated herself by her.</p><p>"I hope you're not getting tired," she said.  There was a minorcadence to the voice, which was rather deep and serious.</p><p>"I don't think I'm tired," said the child, turning eyes ofheavenly blue upon the woman, "but it's dreadful when no one saysa word!"</p><p>"Oh, well, you see," said the woman apologetically, letting asmile creep into her rather bitter face, "we don't know each other."</p><p>"Except you and me," cried the child, with a laugh whichrevealed two rows of minute and pearly teeth.  "We got acquaintedquick, didn't we?"</p><p>"Very," said the woman with flattering gravity.</p><p>"I've come a long way," continued the little one, "and mygrandma cried when I left her.  Here, read this!"  She tugged at astring which ran about her neck, and drew out a tag.  The womanread from it: &#8211;</p><p>"Margaret Samsom, Arline, Colorado."</p><p>"That's my name and where I'm <orig reg="going">go-<pb id="ep.ss.0028.03.jpg" n="789"/>ing</orig>," announced the child.  "And my mamma's name is just thesame as mine.  She'll be waiting for me when I get out of thecoach."</p><p>Her penetrating treble reached the men on the front seat, andUnderwood nudged Victor.</p><p>"D'yeh hear that?" he whispered.  "She's th' daughter of RedMag!"</p><p>They turned in their seats and regarded the child with curiosityand something akin to horror.  She had a face as tender as a flower. Her blue eyes were beaming with excitement, brown ringletsclustered about her low, blue-veined temples, her teeth were likelittle grains of rice, and her parted lips were exquisitely arched.  Asher soft glowing neck crept away between the clean ruffles of hergingham frock, it conveyed an idea of delicacy and loveliness ofperson.  She beamed at the miner as he regarded her with frowninganxiety.</p><p>"Peter's eye!" he said, and spat twice in the road.  At intervalshe ejaculated with disgust, "Red Mag!"  And once he said, "Theonly decent thing for you to do, Hank, is to run this here stage overthe gulch, and end it for her before she meets her 'mamma.'"</p><p>"Have you a tag around your neck?" little Margaret asked ofthe bitter-faced woman.</p><p>"No, dear."</p><p>"What am I going to call you when I want to speak to you?"</p><p>"Mrs. Ellery&#8211;no, aunt Anna."</p><p>The horses were toiling up the slope.  They were in the midstof a great gorge.  The world about them was vast and dead,&#8211;itsfires burned out, its floods spent, its tumult stilled.  As they climbedup and up, the very old woman began to move her head from side toside curiously, and several times she put her hand to her throat.</p><p>"There's a dreadful noise in my ears," she complained.</p><p>"Never bin up as high as this before, I reckon?" said Victorinterrogatively.</p><p>"Who&#8211;me?" piped the old woman.  "No; I've always lived atMorgansport.  That ain't a hilly place."</p><p>"Going to live out this-a-way?"</p><p>"Well, yes, I bethought myself to," responded the old lady in aneighborly tone.  "My sister Marthy, that I've bin livin' with, istwenty years younger than me, and a very spry person.  I got underfoot.  I could see it.  She didn't like me fussin' about her kitchen, nurweedin' in the garden, and it seemed to her that I had to burn a mostuncommon amount of wood to keep warm.  I kin see as plain asanything how it struck Marthy.  I didn't want her grudgin' me mydays, and I took matters in my own hands, and lit right out for myson James's.  I knew Jim would want me!"  She put her head on oneside, exhibiting that last form of coquetry&#8211;that of a mother for awell-loved son.</p><p>"Does your son live at Arline, ma'am?" inquired Victor.</p><p>"Yes," she answered, smiling till her toothless gums were fullyrevealed.  "James Farnam.  Maybe you know him?  He was alwaysgreat for makin' friends."</p><p>Grabo saw the men on the front seat exchange one swift andfrightened look.</p><p>"Now I <hi rend="italic">will</hi> drive the blamed old stage over the rim!"swore Victor to Underwood.  They smiled at each other grimly.</p><p>"What's to pay?" wondered Grabo.</p><p>The day wore on pleasantly enough.  Grabo forgot himself alittle.  Or, rather, the mysticism which was his inheritance from aline of dreamers began to an&#230;sthetize him.  The vastness ofthe world about him, the endurability of those mountain ranges, theclarity of the sapphire heavens, the swing of the high sun, theobvious fret and fume of man's little life as indicated in the groupthere in the coach, all reconciled him somewhat to his grief.  Theold, old woman swayed feebly in her seat, yet still smiled on,thinking of "Jim."  The little child grew<pb id="ep.ss.0028.04.jpg" n="790"/>fretful, and the bitter-faced woman comforted her with infinitetenderness.  The two men on the front seat were telling tales to eachother to pass away the time.  Only the old man and Grabo sat silent. There seemed to be something hunted in the old man's face.</p><p>"What's <hi rend="italic">his</hi> trouble?" wondered Grabo, "and how longbefore oblivion will overtake him?  The trouble with me is, I haveno trouble.  I'm in fit shape for life, and not attaining it."  Heremembered with sudden self-pity that he had not even kissed awoman as men kiss the women they love.  This made him turn theeye of masculine appraisement on the bitter-faced person near him. He noticed that her eyes were gray, half-closed, as if frominstinctive reserve of soul; that her lips were softly compressed, thatthey were shapely and mournful.  Her complexion was that of awoman who has lost anticipation, and in whose veins the bloodmoves wearily.  A plume of gray hair showed above her brow in themidst of the brown.  She was costumed with conspicuous neatnessin black, and about her neck gear was just a touch of brightness, asif, after long denial, she had awakened to the joys of decoration.</p><p>"She's beginning over," mused Grabo.  "She has seen a mirageon the desert, and she's making for it."</p><p>Silence seemed to lie on Grabo like a spell.  The fundamentalsilence of the abyss, of the vault, of the everlasting hills, had comeup and seized him by the throat.  It became a pain at last,&#8211;forGrabo had always been loquacious till he met the Obstacle.  Hemade up his mind to speak, and he turned to the old man.</p><p>"You are going west for the first time, sir?"  He spoke out of adry throat, and the trifling inquiry represented a triumph of will.</p><p>"Me?" said the old man pleasantly, with a kind of timidneighborliness.  "Yes&#8211;the first time.  I've lived in Ohio all mylife."</p><p>"Quite a break-up&#8211;coming away out here," said Grabo.</p><p>"Yes, yes.  Well, I've been living with my son's wife.  My sondied three years ago, and Lucy set out to do her duty by me.  It washard for her&#8211;and harder for me!" he gave a sardonic little twist tohis lips, which were loose and pitiful and discouraged-looking.  "Awhile ago I could see she was taking interest in a man down street, &#8211; a good man, too.  I sold some things I had.  'Lucy,' says I, 'I'mgoing to take myself off.'&#8211;'How'll you live, father?' says she. &#8211;'There's my pension,' says I, 'and there's old Luke Bailey.  He was inmy regiment, you see, and he baches it out in Red Butte.  He's oftenwritten urging me to come out.'&#8211;'But father,' says Lucy, 'I alwayswanted to be with you in your last hours.'  She was still thinking ofher duty.  That's Lucy's style.&#8211;'Lucy,' says I, 'spare yourself thepleasure.  You're a good girl, and that's why I'm getting out of yourway.'"</p><p>His faded eyes watered, and he sat staring at the wall of rockbeside which the coach was running.</p><p>"There ain't nothing so satisfying as being out from underfoot," observed Underwood, who had been listening.</p><p>"It ain't just what I pictured for myself," said the old man. "I've had good homes, and a good wife and children, andresponsibility in my community.  They're all gone.  Sometimes Ithink I never had them,&#8211;that it was a kind o' dream.  Anyhow, nowI'm going on to a new place.  It took sixty-five years for my roots tostrike in, and then I tore 'em up."</p><p>"What's your name, sir?" asked Grabo respectfully.  His heartwarmed genially toward this man who had built up the structure oflife and seen it tumble about his feet.</p><p>"John Siller," responded the man, with a ring in his voice, as ifthe name had its significance.  Grabo was sure it<pb id="ep.ss.0028.05.jpg" n="791"/>was a name which had counted here and there,&#8211;perhaps at townmeetings, perhaps at local elections, maybe in abolition gatherings,certainly on the roster of a volunteer regiment.</p><p>"You've walked a long road," said Grabo gently.</p><p>"Eh?  Oh yes!  Walked a long road!  Well, you'd think so ifyou'd walked it with me.  The people that have passed&#8211;they'dmake a cityful!  But walking a long road ain't the only thing, youngman."</p><p>He looked at Grabo with a penetrating glance.</p><p>"He sees I'm doomed," thought the young man.</p><p>"Walking a road, and not being driven along it, is the thing,"said Anna Ellery.  There was an accent of wrath and sorrow in hervoice.  "My idea is to walk it and set my own pace."</p><p>It had the gusto of a fresh declaration of independence.</p><p>"Evidently," thought Grabo, "she found the path too narrow fortwo."</p><p>It came lunch time, and being in a grove of pines, they allseated themselves on the ground and ate together.  Mrs. Ellery madecoffee; Grabo looked after the child, who was fastidious, and didnot take well to the cold food.  Mrs. Farnam, the old woman, couldnot eat at all, and the coffee she drank intoxicated her.</p><p>"If it wa'n't for the thought of Jim," she gasped again andagain, "I don't know how I could git up spirit to go on."</p><p>"There ain't nothing to do, ma'am, <hi rend="italic">but</hi> git on," saidVictor cheerily.  "You'll come out all right, ma'am."</p><p>But as the afternoon wore on she became more and moredistressed.  Mrs. Ellery noted how the breath fluttered in the poorold throat.  Grabo, who watched her with fascinated eyes, and who &#8211; so strange was his mood&#8211;appeared to feel the winds of Destinyblowing continually upon this party of stragglers in search ofhappiness, saw a peculiar pallor spreading over her face.  He wasnot surprised when the poor little figure toppled forward.  He caughtit in his arms, and called to Victor to rein in.  The brakes clampedthe wheels, and Grabo got out with the old woman in his arms.  Shewas no heavier than a child, but repulsive with the repulsion ofwasted flesh, sunken eyes, and inert limbs.  Her cheeks began topuff out curiously, and her eyes to toll.  The coach was, fortunately,at a small level semicircle of honest horizontal earth.  The soil hadwashed down here, and pi&#241;on trees&#8211;seven in number &#8211;stood together in a confidential and frightened group.  Grabo put theold soul there.  Nay&#8211;the soul, which may have been young or old,had escaped, but whether it was in the purple and solemn valleybeneath them, or in the sweet clarity of daffodil sky above, no manventured to surmise.  All looked at the pitiful body, which, bereft ofthat which gave it its trifling significance, lay supine.</p><p>There being neither prayers nor tears at hand, the bitter-facedwoman, who had been supporting the dead woman, kissed her onthe forehead.</p><p>"Good-by, mother," she said gently.  Grabo felt the tears leapto his eyes.</p><p>"I didn't know women were so sweet," he thought.</p><p>"You heard her say she was goin' to Arline to visit her darlin'son, didn't yeh?" asked Underwood with emotion.</p><p>Grabo nodded.</p><p>"Well," said Underwood, "she wouldn't hev seen him.  He triedto knife Bill Upton in Garey's place three weeks back, and got shotbetween the eyes."</p><p>"Dead?" asked Anna Ellery.</p><p>'You bet, ma'am," said Underwood devoutly.</p><p>"Poor mother!" said Anna Ellery once more.</p><p>The panting beasts stood at rest.  The old man, Siller, washanging on to the child, lest she should go too near the precipice.  Arigor began to creep over the dead woman.</p><pb id="ep.ss.0028.06.jpg" n="792"/><p>"Shall we take her to Arline?" asked Victor.</p><p>Grabo turned sick at the idea.  The old man shivered.  AnnaEllery shook her head.</p><p>"It's no good," she said.  "Whom would we take her to?  This isa beautiful place for a&#8211;for a grave."</p><p>"And handy to heaven," muttered Underwood.</p><p>"How about gettin' through to our journey's end?" asked JohnSiller.</p><p>"We'll have to camp here to-night," Victor said.  "TheRattlesnake River, three miles from here, has been doing its bestlately.  I wouldn't take anybody through it in the dark that I wasanyways responsible for&#8211;not to mention the hosses."  He lookedaffectionately at his beasts.</p><p>"It <hi rend="italic">would</hi> be too bad to risk the horses," smiled Grabo. He was thinking the others might take the Long Voyage merrilyenough.  Yet who could tell!  There is a saying that the young areprodigal of life, but the old economical of it.  Perhaps old manSiller wanted to live!</p><p>"You think, then," said Victor, "that we'd best plant the oldsoul right here?"  He spoke almost tenderly.</p><p>"Not till the child's asleep," whispered Anna Ellery.</p><p>Victor took command, sending Underwood to chop wood, andGrabo to get the victuals from the coach, while he himself lookedafter the horses.</p><p>Anna led the child back among the rocks.</p><p>"See," she said, "you can have a little playhouse here."  Shemade a miniature pantry for her with pebbles and bits of mica forthe dishes.  Then she returned to the "poor mother."  She combedher straggling locks, made her decent, covered her face with a cleanhandkerchief and the whole body with a horse blanket.  By this timethe men had a fire, and a repast with hot coffee.  A good deal oftime had been consumed, and already the shadows were gropingtheir way far down the gorge,&#8211;trooping down like blind menbound on some grim and final errand.  In the inlet of land&#8211;for theblue ether of space ran about them like a fluid sea&#8211;the day beganto gloom.  Anna called the child to her, and they all sat about thefire and ate.  It grew chilly, and she wrapped the child in her cape. When the little one began to fret Anna held her close till she fellasleep, and then carried her over to the shelter of the rocks, andwrapped her well.  When she came back the men had already begunto dig the grave with whatever implements they had at hand.  Therewas one shovel, an axe, and three knives in the party.  They were allutilized for the task, and in a little while the shallow grave was dug. Victor and Grabo laid the old woman in her comfortable bed.  Theycovered her over without the "dust to dust."  No one prayed.  Noone sang.  But Mrs. Ellery had found the dead woman's full nameon a letter within her pocket, and Grabo graved the name on therock.</p><lg><l>MARY FARNAM.  DATE AND PLACE OF BIRTH UNKNOWN.</l><l>DIED ON THE ROAD, AND BURIED BY HER FELLOW TRAVELERS.</l></lg><p>He put the date last.  They all watched him, and stirred the firefrom time to time to give him light.  After it was over, Anna went tolook at the child.  She was sleeping delicately, and when Annastooped close to her she noticed that her breath was like that of ayoung calf.  She came back to the fire and seated herself among themen.  Her eyes were shining, her mouth tender, all her aspectsisterly.</p><p>"Pretty fine little gal, ma'am," said Underwood, pointing overhis shoulder with his thumb.</p><p>"Oh!" said Anna, unable to articulate her appreciation of thechild.</p><p>"You want to know the kindest thing you kin do to her?"persisted Underwood.  Anna's silent gesture answered.</p><pb id="ep.ss.0028.07.jpg" n="793"/><p>"Well, throw her over this here gorge while she sleeps.  She'llnever know nothin' after that."</p><p>"What do you mean?"</p><p>"You ain't acquainted in Arline, ma'am, but if you wus, you'dknow Red Mag.  Every man there knows 'er.  Every woman runsfrom 'er.  She lives in a filthy hut, and talks filthier than she looks. That's the young un's ma."</p><p>"But I won't have it!" Mrs. Ellery cried, clasping her hands.  "Iwon't have her go to a woman like that!"</p><p>She appeared to be shaken by some strange passion.  Grabolistened to the wind wailing through the gorge, but he smiled tohimself, and said that of course it was the windage of Destiny'swings.  For surely this night Her presence was felt.  He turnedgleaming eyes upon Anna.  "Maternity has come to her," hereflected, "without birth pangs."  He was convinced that she wouldnever let the child go to its mother.</p><p>"I like an intelligent breaker of the law," he mused.  He threwhimself back on the ground, his hands under his head.  He washappy.  He liked his companions.  They seemed to him more alivethan any persons he had previously met.</p><p>"The stars are more neighborly than I had supposed," he said,conscious that his calm remark was out of key with Anna's emotion,but willing to take the attention from her.</p><p>"They do look that way out here," admitted Underwood.  "Isuppose it's because they're the only neighbors you kin get."</p><p>"I like the way they mind their own business," observedVictor.  "You'd think, to look at 'em, that they was thicker thansnakes at Slaney's Pocket, but they never git mixed up."</p><p>Grabo was cheerfully misquoting some lines of Tennyson's. Underwood caught the last couplet: &#8211;<quote><lg><l rend="indented">&#8211; "yet with power to burn and brand</l><l rend="indented">His nothingness into man."</l></lg></quote>He debated the point.</p><p>"I don't know about nothingness!" he said.  "When I see theway men come it over these hulking, ugly brutes of mountains, andgit their livings out of 'em, and pick and peck at 'em, and tunnel andbridge 'em, I don't know about nothingness.  I ain't the man to take aback seat fur a star or a mountain."</p><p>The stars seemed to grow in brilliancy.  The blacknessdeepened.  It was impenetrable, chill, yet with streams of warmthflowing through it like currents of charity through a censoriousworld.  The precipice yawned a few feet distant.  The little companyrested at ease on a narrow shelf midway between earth and heaven. They were bound together by the torrent, which impeded theirjourney, by the night which encompassed yet could not extinguishthem, by the new-made grave of their fellow traveler, by thesleeping child, and by the fire.</p><p>"It's odd," said old John Siller, lighting his pipe, "but I don'tknow when I've felt so at home."</p><p>Julian Grabo let his hand fall so that, in the darkness, ittouched Anna Ellery's dress.  He held the fabric between his fingers,as he used to hold his mother's gown when he was a child.</p><p>They all talked together softly, often with a friendlyincoherence.  Anna had a sense of being watched over.  The mensmiled at her brother-wise.  Finally Grabo urged her to sleep, andshe went once more to see to the covering of the child; then shestood for a space by Mary Farnam's grave.  Grabo joined her.</p><p>"<hi rend="italic">She</hi> is well covered," he said.</p><p>"I've been saying a prayer," confessed Anna, "and I'd almostforgotten how."</p><p>"Were you praying for the living or the dead?" asked Grabo.</p><p>"I hardly know," smiled Anna.  "To-night I could easilyimagine that we are all dead."</p><p>Their eyes met.  A shiver of sympathy shook them, and then,with decision,<pb id="ep.ss.0028.08.jpg" n="794"/>they withdrew their gaze.  It is the fashion&#8211;world old&#8211;for soulsthus to salute each other.  These, having saluted, bade each otherfarewell.  Anna lay down beside the child and slept a little while.  Itwas dawn when she awoke, and shafts of marvelous purple lightwere streaming into the uttermost recess of the gorge.  Some farmountains were bathed in rose.  The world was glorious as aTransfiguration.  Anna rose up as one who comes into a new life. The child awoke, too, and laughed at her, dewy-fresh.  They kissed,and while the men were getting ready the horses Anna bathed thelittle one's face and hands, and combed her curls.  Then she madeherself tidy, and had time, before all was in readiness, to cover thegrave of the "fellow traveler" with pi&#241;on boughs.</p><p>Grabo helped her and Margaret into the coach.  Siller sat withGrabo.  Underwood and Victor mounted in front.  The horses hadhad their breakfast, though the people had not, and they started ontheir way with careful speed.  The ford was reached, and theyplunged among foaming waters and hidden rocks.  Little Margaretthrew her arms about Mrs. Ellery's neck with a cry of alarm.  OldSiller grasped Grabo's arm.</p><p>"I believe we're going down," Siller whimpered.</p><p>"I think not," soothed Julian.  "Our friends the horses would beashamed to let us, you know."</p><p>Once more the eyes of Anna and Julian met.  They werewondering the same thing,&#8211;whether it would be a better matter ifthe torrent should overcome them.</p><p>"Life is too sardonic for that," reflected Grabo.  "That innocentbaby will live to grow up under the tutelage of her mother, RedMag; Mrs. Ellery, in her search for liberty, will find some new formof slavery; old Siller will not perish till senility has disintegratedhim; as for me, I shall exist to watch death creeping on me like atide; as for the fellows on the front seat, they wouldn't ruin theirreputations by dying in so innocent a manner!"</p><p>They emerged upon a fine mesa, and sped on swiftly to theplace of relay of horses and breakfast.  At the meal they felt thehour of parting hanging over them heavily.</p><p>"I git tired, sometimes," said Underwood in an outburst, "oflivin' up a gulch.  Strikin' a pile ain't the only thing in life.  It's abouttime I took a little comfort, seems to me, and got a family aboutme."  His eyes rested on Margaret, who had gone into semi-eclipsebehind a bowl of milk.  Her soft curls, her pink chin, and herdimpled hands only were visible.</p><p>"Yes," said old Siller, who was mumbling his food after thefashion of the toothless, "family life's the thing.  If only my son" &#8211;He did not finish, but fixed a wistful gaze on Grabo.</p><p>Julian was, indeed, a good sight to look upon this morning.  Heheld his head high, his eyes were clear and blue, his complexionlike a girl's, his figure elegant, his garments a perfect fit.  He lookedas carefully attired as if he had come newly from his chamber. There was something poignant in the glance Anna turned upon him.</p><p>"If such a man had been my lover"&#8211;she thought brokenly,and then sank into heavy reminiscence.</p><p>"Well," said Victor aloud, "I sometimes think I'd like to settledown, too.  I git tired of drivin' people around."</p><p>He regarded Anna with frank admiration.  Underwoodfollowed his gaze, and for the first time a personal speculation tookpossession of him.  Both of them estimated the woman's excellentphysique, her kind yet sad eyes, the efficiency of her manner, themodest yet striking fashion of her dress.</p><p>When the time came to resume their journey with fresh horses,they had about them that stalwart interest which follows the eatingof a good meal.  The very<pb id="ep.ss.0028.09.jpg" n="795"/>pangs of parting diverted them.  Siller, particularly, was alert.</p><p>"I wonder what old Luke Bailey will think when he sees meloomin' up," he mused, chuckling with anticipatory glee.  "I mean tokeep my settin'-room always spic up for company," he announced. It was intended for a general invitation.</p><p>"So shall I," said Anna in her minor, vibratory voice.  "I shallmake friends of my own choosing.  I shall go to church with goodpeople.  I mean to be useful.  I am going to have some new dresses. After a little while I'm going to invite people to supper."  Shelooked demure, and evidently saw the pitifulness of her spokenaspirations.  "You see," she said by way of explanation, "it's yearssince&#8211;he&#8211;let me hold up my head."</p><p>The words were almost whispered, but every one heard them. A sympathetic silence fell.  No one asked a question, but all fourmen wondered as to the legal status of her liberty.  Margaret wasplaying with some little tassels on Anna's jacket.  She looked up inAnna's face with sudden winsomeness.</p><p>"I like you," she said, and hung her head.  Anna snatched herclose.</p><p>"I like <hi rend="italic">you!</hi>" she declared fiercely.</p><p>Victor turned in his seat.</p><p>"In a little while we'll be at Arline."  The words weresignificant,&#8211;even ominous.</p><p>Anna Ellery must have heard them, but she gave no sign.  Shefixed her eyes upon the landscape, and a peculiar smile fasteneditself upon her face.  Margaret began to yawn, showing thosericelike teeth, and Anna lifted her up into her lap, and absentlysoothed her till she fell asleep.  The curious smile never left herface.</p><p>A few straggling cabins came into view, and then the rawstreets of a mining town.</p><p>"We're here," announced Underwood gloomily.</p><p>There was a gathering in front of the general store,&#8211;ranchers,loafers, Mexicans, Chinese, Indians, Negroes.  The coach stopped,and Victor threw off the mail bag and handed out packages.</p><p>Down the street came a large woman, her arm locked in that ofa male companion.  Both were staggering and vociferous.  Graboguessed the truth instantly.  This was Red Mag,&#8211;this wasMargaret's mother!  He tried once more to think philosophically ofthe wings of Destiny, but he was in hot revolt.  His hands clenchedinvoluntarily.  Old Siller was trembling, and his jaw worked up anddown.</p><p>"Mag's celebratin'," Grabo heard one of the crowd remark.</p><p>"Expectin' her daughter," said a sardonic voice.</p><p>Anna patted the sleeping child, and stared straight ahead.</p><p>A silence spread through the crowd as Mag came staggeringon.  Grabo looked at the bloated face, the dare-devil eyes, thefrowzy red hair, the slovenly gown, and then at the woman whotreasured the child in her arms.</p><p>"I'm going to see an event," he reflected.</p><p>Red Mag seemed to have forgotten temporarily what she hadcome for.  Then, with an oath, she remembered.  She stuck her headin the coach.</p><p>"That's my gal!" she declared.</p><p>Underwood and Victor kept their eyes on Anna, as men in anorchestra fasten their gaze upon the conductor.  Grabo noticed thateach sat with a hand clapped to his pistol pocket.</p><p>"I'm lookin' fur my gal," Mag said defiantly.  Her companioncame forward pugnaciously.</p><p>"Where's that there young un that took passage with you, HankVictor?" he demanded.</p><p>"There's no child here but my daughter," said Anna Ellery inher penetrating voice.</p><p>It was the lift of the b&#226;ton, and the orchestra responded.</p><pb id="ep.ss.0028.10.jpg" n="796"/><p>"Git out of the way, there!" commanded Victor.  He raised hiswhip.  Mag began to pour forth oaths fluently.  But the whip fell. The horses leaped from the watering trough, their check reinshanging.</p><p>A mile out of town, Grabo leaned forward, lifted one of AnnaEllery's hands where it still clasped the sleeping child, and put it tohis lips.  Old Siller was weeping.  Underwood and Victor sat closetogether on the front seat and seemed to be enjoying themselves.</p><p>In an hour they reached Grabo's place.  It was the cross-roadson a high and sunny plain, where the pungent smell of sage-brushperfumed the air.  Grabo looked about him, in the spirit ofreconnaissance.  He had a sense that he was to be left in space.  Buthe liked it.</p><p>There was an open wagon and a pair of mules waiting for him,and they were driven by an alert boy with freckles.</p><p>"I came down yisterday," he said to Grabo, "expectin' you. When you didn't come, I camped.  Mr. Memory is awful anxious tosee ye, sir.  He's laid up with a twisted knee.  Got throwed off hisbronc."</p><p>"You see I'm wanted," Grabo smiled at Siller.  "And I thinkyou'll be!"</p><p>He shook hands with all the men, and they slapped him on theshoulder.  He and Anna looked once more in each other's eyes.  Fora second or two they were motionless.  Then he removed a curiouslittle pin from the inside of his coat, regarded its cabalistic insigniaaffectionately, and pinned it on her dress.</p><p>"It's a decoration for distinguished conduct," he said with suchnonchalance as he had at command.</p><p>He kissed Margaret on her moist forehead.</p><p>"She'll grow up a good woman," he prophesied.  "She'll be acomfort to you.  In a day or two I shall send her a gift.  Once inthree months it will be repeated.  Perhaps you'll write me how shegets on."</p><p>He was, indeed, laying plans for the child even as he talked. The freckled boy transferred Julian's belongings to the wagon.</p><p>"Sometimes when you drive by I'll be here at the cross-roads toyell at you," Grabo told Victor.</p><p>He got in the wagon, and both vehicles started on their ways.</p><p>For a few moments Grabo sat tense, throbbing with curiousemotions.</p><p>Then twelve shots rent the air,&#8211;the parting salute of hisfellow travelers.  He stood up in the wagon and waved his adieux. He could see Anna waving, and little Margaret, whom the shootinghad awakened, and he recognized Siller's bandana.  When he satdown the freckled boy said,&#8211;</p><p>"You'll git jest as hearty a hullo when ye reach Amber Ranch."</p><p>"Shall I?" cried Grabo.  "And who are you, friend?"</p><p>"Me?  Biff Hathaway.  I'm herdin' f'r Mr. Memory.  I come outhere to die.  The doctor giv me a month."</p><p>"How long ago was that?" asked Grabo.</p><p>"Four year," grinned the freckled boy.</p><p>Grabo straightened his shoulders.  He took in the flowingspacious plain, the perfect arch of the cloudless vault, the windingsof the persistent road.</p><p>"Doesn't it seem to you we're taking it a little too easy?" heasked.</p><p>The freckle-faced boy snapped his whip, and the tawny mulesleaped forward.  Julian sat straining his eyes into the distance. Miraculously, the common dust of the highway had beentransmuted into gold.</p><closer><signed><hi rend="italic">Elia W. Peattie.</hi></signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI>