<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD peattie.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include/peattie.dtd" [
<!NOTATION jpeg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY ep.child.intro.01 SYSTEM "ep.child.intro.01.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ep.child.intro.02 SYSTEM "ep.child.intro.02.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>

<TEI id="ep.child.intro">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Youth and America: Elia Peattie's Stories for Children and Young
                    Adults</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author n="Crockett, Carrie">Crockett, Carrie</author>
                <principal>George-Bloomfield, Susanne, 1947-</principal>
                <editor/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Project Team</resp>
                    <name>Zach Bajaber</name>
                    <name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
                    <name>Laura Weakly</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2009</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska Center for Digital Research in the
                    Humanities</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
                <address>
<addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
                <idno>ep.child.intro</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Original.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>


        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords n="genre">
<term>Commentary</term>
</keywords>
</textClass></profileDesc>



        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-27</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Laura Weakly</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Initial encoding</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>

            <div1>

                <p>
                    <xptr n="child_links.html"/>
                </p>

                <div2>
                    <head type="main">Youth and America: Elia Peattie's Stories for Children and
                        Young Adults</head>


                    <p>
                        <figure entity="ep.child.intro.01">
                            <figDesc/>
                        </figure> One of the marks of Elia Peattie's versatility was her ability to
                        move effortlessly not only between genres but also reading
                        audiences. In addition to the hundreds of stories, reviews, and novels she
                        wrote for adults, Peattie created dozens of books and stories for her
                        younger readers, America's children, the kinds of stories her own three
                        children would enjoy. Her first known published work for children was an
                        1887 short story, "Grizel Cochrane's Ride," an historical account of the
                        Monmouth rebellion, for <hi rend="italic">St. Nicholas</hi> followed by an
                        illustrated history of the United States, <hi rend="italic">Our Land of
                            Liberty, or The Wonderful Story of America</hi>, published in 1895.
                        Among her young adult novels are a series of books about Azalea, a girl from
                        the Blue Ridge Mountains, and two that were first serialized in the <hi
                            rend="italic">Youth's Companion</hi>.</p>

                    <p>Peattie's work reflects the multi-faceted experience of childhood in the late
                        nineteenth century, especially those living in rapidly changing,
                        industrializing cities. Sometimes her youthful characters admired the great,
                        mechanical marvels of the age, the trains, and occasionally they traveled in
                        them westward across unfamiliar terrain, faces pressed against their
                        windows, hope in the future high. "Prairie, prairie, prairie, as far as the
                        eye could see . . . the sky was blurred with dust, the silence
                            absolute."<ref target="n01" n="1">1</ref> She wrote of families lost and
                        of families found, of friendships and courtships and sorrow. Her characters
                        studied in schools, planted and dreamed in gardens, and worked countless
                        types of jobs. Notwithstanding the circumstances surrounding each of her
                        young characters, however, Peattie was quick to point out the power each
                        possessed to be the innovator of his or her own future. "It is never quite
                        possible to tell what the human brain is going to do. Even the possessor
                        knows little about its vagaries," she wrote in "The Family He Found,"
                        published in <hi rend="italic">The Youth's Companion</hi> in 1900. Helen
                        Walden, a character in another short story, "The Fourth Chaperon," whose
                        childhood had required her to work instead of receive an education, had
                        nonetheless imagined a better path and staunchly followed it. "Here, when
                        school had been denied her, and heavy burdens of housekeeping and child
                        tending and sewing had been put upon her, she used to come in the evenings,
                        and cowering under the army blankets, study and read. There was no one to
                        guide her. She took what came to hand. She made the most of everything."<ref
                            target="n02" n="2">2</ref></p>

                    <p>Peattie believed that children's fiction should accurately mirror their real
                        lives instead of present adult constructions of the childhood realm. She
                        decried those authors who "did not follow the processes of a child's mind
                        with any more accuracy than [they] followed the evolution of a star."<ref
                            target="n03" n="3">3</ref> Fortunately, several magazines came into
                        existence during the latter part of the nineteenth century that also
                        subscribed to Peattie's viewpoint. <hi rend="italic">St. Nicholas
                            Magazine</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Youth's Companion</hi>, and <hi
                            rend="italic">Wide Awake</hi> published literature expressly for youth
                        that was written by some of the most esteemed literary figures of the day.
                        Of these periodicals, which refused to marginalize American childhood,
                        Peattie was moved to write in the <hi rend="italic">Omaha World Herald</hi>,
                        "The child knew presently what it was to see childhood pictured, by artists
                        and by writers. It saw that its joys, its tears, its temptations had at last
                        come to be appreciated. It saw at last that there were those who knew how
                        deeply children could love and hate; how brave they could be; how
                        sacrificial; how happy. The world that they had peopled with things not seen
                        with the eye was reproduced . . . they no longer had that dragging sense of
                        insignificance to which they had been accustomed."<ref target="n04" n="4"
                            >4</ref></p>

                    <p><figure entity="ep.child.intro.02">
                            <figDesc/>
                        </figure>Peattie's belief in the importance of telling children's stories is
                        interwoven throughout her work. One example can be found in her novel-length
                        fairy tale, <hi rend="italic">Edda and the Oak</hi>, which narrates the
                        journey of a young girl as she travels from her home, a large city, to her
                        grandmother's farm in the West. The child subsequently is delighted to
                        discover that her grandmother's garden is indeed more than it seems, for
                        within it is an enchanted fairy realm that can be crossed into by night.</p>

                    <p>Edda, an archetype of the developing American child, bears little resemblance
                        to many of the youths from European literature who stumble upon magical
                        realms. Instead of desiring the use the fairies' magic for her own gain, she
                        makes a quick study of their culture and aids her new acquaintances in
                        finding solutions to perplexing concerns of their kingdom. At one point in
                        the tale, when Edda is introduced to the fairy queen, Peattie emphasizes the
                        importance of the child understanding not only her own worth but also the
                        worth of her own story.</p>

                    <p>The queen raised a pair of gold lorgnettes and looked at Edda long and
                        hard.</p>

                    <p>"Come," she said, "you seem an interesting child. Are you?"</p>

                    <p>"I don't know," said Edda in a rather silly way. There were hundreds of
                        little creatures listening, and she could hear the elves giggling at the
                        question.</p>

                    <p>"Don't you interest yourself?" asked the queen.</p>

                    <p>Edda nodded, and felt herself blushing redder and redder.</p>

                    <p>"Then you will probably interest me. Come child, walk with me, and tell me
                        all the story of your life."</p>

                    <p>"Oh, are we going on a <hi rend="italic">very</hi> long walk?"</p>

                    <p>So she talked as hard and as fast as she could, and it's really a fact that,
                        by talking so fast that her tongue ached, she was able, by the time the
                        maids had clothed her in a moonlight-blue satin, hung over with threads of
                        silver delicate as cobwebs, to tell Goldheart almost everything there was to
                        tell about herself."<ref target="n05" n="5">5</ref></p>

                    <p>It seems quite deliberate that Peattie emphasizes not only the importance of
                        knowing and preserving a child's story, but also the value of the child
                        telling her story in her own voice. This great respect for children's minds,
                        their experiences, and their inestimable worth as contributors to society
                        formed the basis of Peattie's approach to creating their literature. She
                        wrote in 1895, " . . . if vistas are to be opened up to the mind, the
                        library . . . must not be limited . . . as soon as possible I would lead the
                        mind of either boy or girl to the classics and I would encourage them to
                        read books that relate to achievement. I would give them lofty ideals. The
                        daily stress of living will lower their ideals fast enough at best . . . it
                        is not for any one to set bounds and metes for her. She may have a capacity
                        for comprehension which the purchaser of the library never possessed. The
                        human soul comes soon to its own responsibility. The human mind runs to its
                            liberty."<ref target="n06" n="6">6</ref></p>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1>
                <head>Bibliography of Writing for Children<lb/> by<lb/> Elia Wilkinson
                    Peattie</head>

                <div2>
                    <head type="sub">~Books~</head>
                    <bibl><title level="m">America in War and Peace</title>. Chicago: W.B. Conkey,
                        1898.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">Azalea: The Story of a Girl in the Blue Ridge
                            Mountains</title>. Chicago: Reilly, 1912.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">Annie Laurie and Azalea</title>. Chicago: Reilly and
                        Britton, 1913.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">Azalea at Sunset Gap</title>. Chicago: Reilly and
                        Britton, 1912, 1914.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">Azalea's Silver Web</title>. Chicago: Reilly and Britton,
                        1915.</bibl>
                    <bibl><xref n="ep.nov.EatO">
                            <title level="m">Edda and the Oak</title>
                        </xref>. Chicago: Rand, McNally, 1911. Also published in A Christmas Party
                        for Santa Claus by Ida Huntington (Rand McNally 1912).</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">Lotta Embury's Career</title>. Boston: Houghton Mifflin,
                        1915.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">The Newcomers</title>. Boston: Houghton Mifflin,
                        1917.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">Our Chosen Land: A Romantic Story of America from the
                            Time of its Discovery and Conquest to the Present Day. An Interesting
                            Account of the Progress and Development of Our Country, Written
                            Especially for Young Folks.</title> Chicago: Wabash, 1896. [An
                        abridgment of the author's Story of America].</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">Our Land of Liberty, or The Wonderful Story of America,
                            Containing the Romantic Incidents of History, from the Discovery of
                            America to the Present Time</title>. Chicago: International Publishing
                        Company, 1895.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">The Pictorial Story of America Containing the Romantic
                            Incidents of History from the Discovery of America to the Present
                            Time</title>. Chicago: Amer. Pub. and Engraving, 1895; Union Pub., 1896;
                        National Pub., 1896, Tombaugh Publications, 1982.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">Pictorial Story of America: Part 3 Fulton County,
                            Indiana</title>. Chicago: National Pub, 1896.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">Sarah Brewster's Relatives</title>. Boston: Houghton
                        Mifflin, 1916.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">The Story of America : Containing the Romantic Incidents
                            of History, from the Discovery of America to the Present Time</title>.
                        San Francisco: R.S. King, 1889; Chicago: Mid-continent Pub., 1891, 1892;
                        Cleveland: Neff, 1893; Chicago: W.B. Conkey, 1898.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">With Scrip and Staf: A Tale of the Children's
                            Crusade</title>. New York: A.D.F. Randolph, 1891.</bibl>
                </div2>

                <div2>
                    <head type="sub">~Collections~</head>
                    <bibl><title level="m">Ickery Ann and Other Girls and Boys</title>. Chicago:
                        H.S. Stone, 1899. Includes short stories: "Ickery Ann," "The Genius,"
                        "Grizel Cochrane's Ride." "Bertha's Debut," "The Shut-ins," "The Message of
                        the Lilies," "The McCulloughs of the Bluff," "Tarts," "Jock, the Chipmunk,"
                        "How Christmas Came to the Santa Maria Flats," "Christmas at Goldberg," "The
                        Dead Letter," "The Wooing of Fan Tod," "The Breeziest Reunion," and "Tommy,
                        the Beach Cat."</bibl>
                </div2>

                <div2>
                    <head type="sub">~Stories and Poems~</head>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"At Aunt Frank's Service."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (1 Feb. 1900):49.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"At Dr. Merriwether's Service."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (11 Aug. 1904):374.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Barbara's Valentine."</title>
                        <title level="j">St. Nicholas</title> (13 Feb. 1902):76.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Bertha's Debut."</title>
                        <title level="j">St. Nicholas</title> 17 (Jan. 1890):217-221. </bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"The Color Bearers."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (17 Sept. 1914):477.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"A Declaration of Independence."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (10 Dec. 1903):619.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"The Disgrace of Grandfather."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (7 Sept. 1916):492.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Dressmaking."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (5 July 1917):377.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"The Family He Found."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (25 Jan. 1900):37.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"The Fourth Chaperone."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (28 Sept. 1905):448.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Grandmother's Fete."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (2 Oct. 1902):470.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Grizel Cochrane's Ride: Founded on an Incident of the
                            Monmouth Rebellion."</title>
                        <title level="j">St. Nicholas</title> 14 (Feb. 1887):271-278.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"The Home Road."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (26 Aug. 1915):429-430. </bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"How Bet Came to Her Own."</title>
                        <title level="j">Brown Book of Boston</title> June 1904 (vol 9.2).</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Kenyon's Bride."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (7 Jan. 1904):1.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"The Last Sedan-Chair."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (22 Feb. 1906):85.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"The Lion Light."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (1 Nov. 1917):621-622.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"The Little Brides of Tryon."</title> [poem] <title
                            level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (28 July 1921): 412.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Lotta Embury's Career."</title> (Serial) <title
                            level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (10 Dec. 1914 through 11 Jan.
                        1915).</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"The McCulloughs of the Bluff."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (16 June 1898):285-286.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"The Mean Little Town."</title> (Serial) <title level="j"
                            >Youth's Companion</title> (5 Oct. 1916 through 7 Dec. 1916).</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"In Memoriam."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (30 May 1912):281.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Message of the Lillies."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (7 Apr. 1898):161-162.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Old Kaskaskia."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (21 Apr. 1904):196.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"The Pageant."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (2 Aug. 1917):430.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Sarah Brewster's Relatives."</title> (Serial) <title
                            level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (24 July 1913 through 25 Sept.
                        1913.)</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"A Singing Bird."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (20 June 1912):331.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Some Odd Figurines."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (10 Oct. 1901):491.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Tapestry."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (18 June 1903):293.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Tarts."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (21 Apr. 1898):191.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"True Hospitality."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (19 Apr. 1900):215.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"The Utilization of Uncle Reginald."</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (25 May 1899):262.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Wan Tsze-King".</title>
                        <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title> (2 June 1901):229-230.</bibl>
                </div2>

                <div2>
                    <head type="sub">~Collected in Anthologies~</head>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Grizel Cochrane's Ride: Founded on an Incident of the
                            Monmouth Rebellion."</title> H<title level="m">eroines of History and
                            Legend: Stories and Poems.</title> Ed. Elva S. Smith. Boston: Lothrop,
                        Lee, and Shepard, 1921.</bibl>
                    <bibl>"<title level="a">How Christmas Came to the Santa Maria Flats."</title>
                            C<title level="m">hildren's Book of Christmas Stories.</title> Ed. Asa
                        Don Dickinson. Garden City, NY: Children's Crimson Series, 1913.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Grizel Cochrane's Ride."</title>
                        <title level="m">Heroines of History and Legend</title>. Ed. Elva S. Smith.
                        Lothrop, Lee, &amp; Shepard, 1921.</bibl>
</div2>
<div2>

                    <head type="sub">~Selected Book Reviews ~</head>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"100 Books for Girls."</title>
                        <title level="m">Omaha World-Herald</title> (14 Apr. 1895):18.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Mrs. Wiggin's Delightful 'Rebecca': A Study of Girl Life
                            in New England."</title>
                        <title level="j">Chicago Tribune</title> 3 Oct. 1903:13.</bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="a">"Kate Douglas Wiggin."</title>
                        <title level="j">Chicago Tribune</title> 17 Sept 1904:7.</bibl>
                </div2>
            </div1>



            <div1>
                <head type="sub">References</head>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Peattie, Elia</author>. <title level="a">"About Children's
                        Books."</title>
                    <title level="j">Omaha World Herald</title>. 7/16/1893. p.16</bibl>

                <bibl> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;. <title level="a">"Easter Lilies and
                        Girls."</title>
                    <title level="j">Omaha World Herald</title>. 4/14/95, p. 18.</bibl>

                <bibl> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;. <title level="m">Edda and the Oak.</title>
                    Chicago: Rand, McNally &amp; Co. 1911.</bibl>

                <bibl> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;. <title level="a">"The Family He
                        Found."</title>
                    <title level="j">The Youth's Companion</title>. 1/25/1900. p.1</bibl>

                <bibl> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;. <title level="a">"The Fourth Chaperon
                        [sic]."</title>
                    <title level="j">Youth's Companion</title>. 9/28/05. P. 448</bibl>

                <bibl> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;. <title level="a">"The Home Road."</title>
                    <title level="j">The Youth's Companion</title>. 8/26/1915.</bibl>
            </div1>

            <div1>
                <head type="sub">Illustrations</head>

                <bibl> "The Crow Telling the Secret to Edda." from <title level="m">Edda and the
                        Oak</title> by Elia W. Peattie, Pictures by Katherine Merrill.Chicago: Rand,
                    McNally &amp; Co, 1911:132</bibl>

                <bibl> "And then came Azalea." from <title level="m">Azalea: The Story of a Girl in
                        the Blue Ridge Mountains</title>. Chicago: Reilly &amp; Britton, 1912:
                    Frontispiece.</bibl>
            </div1>


            <div1>
                <head type="sub">Notes</head>

                <p><note id="n01" n="1">1</note>Peattie "Home Road" 1.</p>
                <p><note id="n02" n="2">2</note>Peattie "Fourth" 448.</p>
                <p><note id="n03" n="3">3</note>Peattie "Family" 1.</p>
                <p><note id="n04" n="4">4</note>Peattie "About" 16.</p>
                <p><note id="n05" n="5">5</note>Peattie <hi rend="italic">Edda</hi> 48, 49-50.</p>
                <p><note id="n06" n="6">6</note>Peattie "Easter" 18.</p>
            </div1>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
