<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD peattie.dtd (Nebraska Press)//EN" "include/peattie.dtd" [

]>
<TEI id="ep.gs.0006">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Story of An Obstinate Corpse</title>
<title type="sub"></title>
<author n="Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935">Peattie, Elia Wilkinson, 1862-1935</author>
<principal>George-Bloomfield, Susanne, 1947-</principal>
<editor></editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Team</resp>
<name>Zach Bajaber</name>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Nebraska Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</publisher>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>ep.gs.0006</idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<!-- <notesStmt>
<note></note>
</notesStmt> -->

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author n="Peattie, Elia W.">Elia W. Peattie</author>
<title level="m">The Shape of Fear and Other Ghostly Tales</title>
<title level="a">Story of An Obstinate Corpse</title>
<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
<publisher>Macmillan</publisher>
<date value="1898">1898</date>
<series>Short Story Index Reprint Series</series>
<pubPlace>Freeport, NY</pubPlace>
<publisher>Books for Libraries Press</publisher>
<date value="1969">1969</date>
<biblScope type="pages">67-75</biblScope>
</bibl>

</sourceDesc>

<!-- <notesStmt>
<note></note>
</notesStmt> -->
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords n="genre">
<term>Short Story</term>
</keywords>
</textClass></profileDesc>


<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2009-02-26</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Vicki Martin</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Proofreading</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2008-11-17</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Nicholas Swiercek</name>
</respStmt>
<item></item>
</change>
<change>
<date>2007-10-31</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted from html</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>200y-mm-dd</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Transcribed by Judy Boss</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Original Transcription</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1>

<pb id="ep.gs.0006.01.jpg" n="67"/>

<head>STORY OF AN OBSTINATE CORPSE</head>

<p>VIRGIL HOYT is a photographer's assistant up at St. Paul, and

enjoys his work without being consumed by it. He has been in

search of the picturesque all over the West and hundreds of miles to

the north, in Canada, and can speak three or four Indian dialects and

put a canoe through the rapids.   That is to say, he is a man of

adventure, and no dreamer. He can fight well and shoot better, and

swim so as to put up a winning race with the Indian boys, and he

can sit in the saddle all day and not worry about it to-morrow.</p>

<p>Wherever he goes, he carries a camera.</p>

<p>"The world," Hoyt is in the habit of saying to those who sit with

him when he smokes his pipe, "was created in six days to be <orig reg="photographed">pho-

<pb id="ep.gs.0006.02.jpg" n="68"/>

tographed</orig>. Man&#8212;and particularly woman&#8212;was made for the same

purpose. Clouds are not made to give moisture nor trees to cast

shade. They have been created in order to give the camera obscura

something to do."</p>

<p>In short, Virgil Hoyt's view of the world is whimsical, and he

likes to be bothered neither with the disagreeable nor the

mysterious. That is the reason he loathes and detests going to a

house of mourning to photograph a corpse. The bad taste of it

offends him; but above all, he doesn't like the necessity of

shouldering, even for a few moments, a part of the burden of sorrow

which belongs to some one else.   He dislikes sorrow, and would

willingly canoe five hundred miles up the cold Canadian rivers to

get rid of it. Nevertheless, as assistant photographer, it is often his

duty to do this very kind of thing.</p>

<p>Not long ago he was sent for by a rich Jewish family to

photograph the remains of the mother, who had just died. He was

put out, but he was only an assistant, and he went. 

<pb id="ep.gs.0006.03.jpg" n="69"/>

He was taken to the front parlor, where the dead woman lay in her

coffin. It was evident to him that there was some excitement in the

household, and that a discussion was going on. But Hoyt said to

himself that it didn't concern him, and he therefore paid no attention

to it.</p>

<p>The daughter wanted the coffin turned on end in order that the

corpse might face the camera properly, but Hoyt said he could

overcome the recumbent attitude and make it appear that the face

was taken in the position it would naturally hold in life, and so they

went out and left him alone with the dead.</p>

<p>The face of the deceased was a strong and positive one, such as

may often be seen among Jewish matrons. Hoyt regarded it with

some admiration, thinking to himself that she was a woman who

had known what she wanted, and who, once having made up her

mind, would prove immovable. Such a character appealed to Hoyt.

He reflected that he might have married if only he could have found

a woman 

<pb id="ep.gs.0006.04.jpg" n="70"/>

with strength of character sufficient to disagree with him. There was

a strand of hair out of place on the dead woman's brow, and he

gently pushed it back. A bud lifted its head too high from among the

roses on her breast and spoiled the contour of the chin, so he broke

it off.   He remembered these things later with keen distinctness,

and that his hand touched her chill face two or three times in the

making of his arrangements.</p>

<p>Then he took the impression, and left the house.</p>

<p>He was busy at the time with some railroad work, and several

days passed before he found opportunity to develop the plates.  He

took them from the bath in which they had lain with a number of

others, and went energetically to work upon them, whistling some

very saucy songs he had learned of the guide in the Red River

country, and trying to forget that the face which was presently to

appear was that of a dead woman.   He had used three plates as a

precaution against accident, 

<pb id="ep.gs.0006.05.jpg" n="71"/>

and they came up well. But as they developed, he became aware of

the existence of something in the photograph which had not been

apparent to his eye in the subject. He was irritated, and without

attempting to face the mystery, he made a few prints and laid them

aside, ardently hoping that by some chance they would never be

called for.</p>

<p>However, as luck would have it,&#8212;and Hoyt's luck never had

been good,&#8212;his employer asked one day what had become of those

photographs.   Hoyt tried to evade making an answer, but the effort

was futile, and he had to get out the finished prints and exhibit

them. The older man sat staring at them a long time.</p>

<p>"Hoyt," he said, "you're a young man, and very likely you have

never seen anything like this before. But I have. Not exactly the

same thing, perhaps, but similar phenomena have come my way a

number of times since I went in the business, and I want to tell you

there are things in heaven and earth not dreamt of&#8212;"</p>

<pb id="ep.gs.0006.06.jpg" n="72"/>

<p>"Oh, I know all that tommy-rot," cried Hoyt, angrily, "but when

anything happens I want to know the reason why and how it is

done."</p>

<p>"All right," answered his employer, "then you might explain

why and how the sun rises."</p>

<p>But he humored the young man sufficiently to examine with

him the baths in which the plates were submerged, and the plates

themselves. All was as it should be; but the mystery was there, and

could not be done away with.</p>

<p>Hoyt hoped against hope that the friends of the dead woman

would somehow forget about the photographs; but the idea was

unreasonable, and one day, as a matter of course, the daughter

appeared and asked to see the pictures of her mother.</p>

<p>"Well, to tell the truth," stammered Hoyt, "they didn't come out

quite&#8212;quite as well as we could wish."</p>

<p>"But let me see them," persisted the lady. "I'd like to look at

them anyhow."</p>

<pb id="ep.gs.0006.07.jpg" n="73"/>

<p>"Well, now," said Hoyt, trying to be soothing, as he believed it

was always best to be with women,&#8212;to tell the truth he was an

ignoramus where women were concerned,&#8212;"I think it would be

better if you didn't look at them.  There are reasons why&#8212;" he

ambled on like this, stupid man that he was, till the lady naturally

insisted upon seeing the pictures without a moment's delay.</p>

<p>So poor Hoyt brought them out and placed them in her hand,

and then ran for the water pitcher, and had to be at the bother of

bathing her forehead to keep her from fainting.</p>

<p>For what the lady saw was this: Over face and flowers and the

head of the coffin fell a thick veil, the edges of which touched the

floor in some places.  It covered the features so well that not a hint

of them was visible.</p>

<p>"There was nothing over mother's face!" cried the lady at

length.</p>

<p>"Not a thing," acquiesced Hoyt.   "I know, because I had

occasion to touch her 

<pb id="ep.gs.0006.08.jpg" n="74"/>

face just before I took the picture. I put some of her hair back from

her brow."</p>

<p>"What does it mean, then?" asked the lady.</p>

<p>"You know better than I. There is no explanation in science.

Perhaps there is some in&#8212;in psychology."</p>

<p>"Well," said the young woman, stammering a little and

coloring, "mother was a good woman, but she always wanted her

own way, and she always had it, too."</p>

<p>"Yes."</p>

<p>"And she never would have her picture taken. She didn't admire

her own appearance. She said no one should ever see a picture of

her."</p>

<p>"So?" said Hoyt, meditatively.   "Well, she's kept her word,

hasn't she?"</p>

<p>The two stood looking at the photographs for a time. Then Hoyt

pointed to the open blaze in the grate.</p>

<p>"Throw them in," he commanded. "Don't let your father see

them&#8212;don't keep them 

<pb id="ep.gs.0006.09.jpg" n="75"/>

yourself. They wouldn't be agreeable things to keep."</p>

<p>"That's true enough," admitted the lady. And she threw them in

the fire. Then Virgil Hoyt brought out the plates and broke them

before her eyes.</p>

<p>And that was the end of it&#8212;except that Hoyt sometimes tells

the story to those who sit beside him when his pipe is lighted.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>